<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>1</num>
  <heading>Rules Of Civil Procedure Code Of The Lac Courte Oreilles Band Of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</heading>
  <text>Preamble</text>
  <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, Article V, § 1 (q) and (s) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "establish a tribal court for the purpose of enforcing tribal ordinance…" Article V, § 1 (q); "promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and provide for the maintenance of law and order and the administration of justice by establishing a tribal court and defining its duties and powers" Article V, § 1 (s). The following rules are adopted to govern civil proceedings initiated in the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court.</text>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.1</num>
    <heading>Introduction</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.101</num>
      <heading>Title</heading>
      <text>This ordinance shall be known as the Rules of Civil Procedure Code of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.102</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, Article V, § 1 (q) and (s) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "establish a tribal court for the purpose of enforcing tribal ordinance…" Article V, § 1 (q); "promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and provide for the maintenance of law and order and the administration of justice by establishing a tribal court and defining its duties and powers" Article V, § 1 (s).</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.103</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this ordinance is to establish the Rules of Civil Procedure and practice before the courts of the Tribe.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.104</num>
      <heading>Territorial Applicability</heading>
      <text>This ordinance shall govern the sovereign immunity of the Tribe pursuant to the provisions of this ordinance within Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation lands as well as off-reservation lands under the jurisdiction and purview of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.105</num>
      <heading>Effective Date</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections; the provisions of this ordinance shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.106</num>
      <heading>Interpretation</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this ordinance:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be interpreted and applied as the minimum requirements to secure a just, speedy and inexpensive determination of every action and proceeding;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At every state of the proceeding, the court may disregard any technical error or defect in a failure to comply with these rules which does not affect the substantive rights of the parties particularly those not represented by an attorney.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.107</num>
      <heading>Severability And Non-Liability</heading>
      <text>If any section, provision or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this ordinance.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.108</num>
      <heading>Repeal Of Inconsistent Tribal Ordinances</heading>
      <text>All ordinances and resolutions inconsistent with this ordinance are hereby repealed. To the extent that this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, code, ordinance or regulation, the provisions of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.2</num>
    <heading>Definitions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.201</num>
      <heading>General Definitions</heading>
      <text>Any term not defined in this Section shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><strong>"Appellate Court"</strong> shall mean the appellate court as designated in 2 LCOTCL Chapter 4 – Appellate Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><strong>"Arrest Warrant"</strong> shall mean an order in writing issued by a tribal judge directing authorized personnel to arrest the person designated in a warrant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"<strong>Citizen</strong>" shall mean those persons whom are currently citizens (members) of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and those who are entitled to be citizens (members) under provisions in effect, or who fall within the class defined as citizens (members) in Article II of the Constitution of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text><strong>"Clerk of Court"</strong> shall mean an officer of the Tribal Court who has charge of the clerical part of its business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text><strong>"Complaint"</strong> shall mean a formal, written allegation against a party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text><strong>"Juvenile"</strong> shall mean any individual less than eighteen (18) years of age.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"<strong>Reservation" or "Reservation Lands"</strong> means those lands, including the beds of any streams and flowages, located within the exterior boundaries of the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation lands as well as off-reservation lands under the jurisdiction and purview of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text><strong>"Subpoena"</strong> shall mean a writ commanding the designated person to appear and testify and/or produce physical evidence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text><strong>"Search Warrant"</strong> shall mean an order in writing issued by a tribal judge directing authorized tribal enforcement personnel to search specific persons and/or property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"<strong>Tribal Court</strong>" shall mean the duly constituted court of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, as established by the Tribal Governing Board, with the judicial authority of the Tribe pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution 76-10, dated May 27, 1976.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"<strong>Tribal Governing Board</strong>" shall be the duly constituted Tribal Governing Board of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to Article III of the Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"<strong>Tribal Law Enforcement Officer</strong>" shall mean any personnel who currently is employed by the Tribe as a Police Officer or Conservation Warden pursuant to 10 LCOTCL Chapter 1 – Public Safety Commission Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text><strong>"Tribe"</strong> shall mean the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.3</num>
    <heading>Establishment And Duties Of The Court</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.301</num>
      <heading>Creation Of The Court</heading>
      <text>There is hereby established the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.302</num>
      <heading>Jurisdiction Of The Tribal Court</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Court shall have jurisdiction over:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All matters arising under the Constitution and laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All actions brought under the provisions of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code of Law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All other civil actions in which the locus of any element of any claim is on the Tribe's reservation, or which is based on any contract made on or providing for the delivery of goods or services on the reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code of Law, the Tribal Court shall have jurisdiction in claims, counterclaims, or cross-claims 	 Tribe or its officers acting in their official capacity only as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Against the Tribe, an action for a writ of habeas corpus to test the legality of a person's detention by the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Against an officer of the Tribe for actions taken within his or her official capacity, an action for prospective relief in which the officer has acted beyond the scope of his or her valid authority, in violation of applicable law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Against the Tribe, or against an officer of the Tribe for actions taken within his or her official capacity, where the Tribe has properly waived its sovereign immunity or that of its officers, by resolution, ordinance, agreement, or otherwise.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.303</num>
      <heading>Consent To Jurisdiction</heading>
      <text>Anyone entering the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation consents to the civil jurisdiction of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court and such criminal jurisdiction as is not prohibited by federal law, and the application of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code of Law regulating conduct while upon the reservation.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.304</num>
      <heading>Composition Of The Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court</heading>
      <text>All judicial authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians shall be vested in the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court. The Tribal Court shall be composed of the Justices, Judges, and Magistrates of the Tribal Court, Court Administrator, the Clerk of Court, Deputy Clerks and other judicial employees.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.305</num>
      <heading>Location Of Lac Courte Oreilles Court</heading>
      <text>The seat of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court shall be the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation. The Court may convene in any location designated by the Tribal Governing Board or a judge or magistrate of the Court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.306</num>
      <heading>Law Applicable To Civil Actions</heading>
      <text>In all civil actions, the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court shall apply any ordinance of the Tribe, the applicable laws of the United States, and any federal regulations which may be applicable. For any matter not determined by the law of the Tribe, the American Law Institute's Concise Restatement of Torts, Concise Restatement of Property, Restatement (2d) Contracts, and the Uniform Commercial Code shall be used as authority to the extent applicable, subject to modification by the Court to reflect the customs, traditions, values and policies of the Tribe. The Court shall make such modification only upon a finding, made after notice and hearing, that modification is necessary to conform to the law to the customs, traditions, values, or policies of the Tribe. The Court may of its own motion or that of a party, adopt any other source of law as persuasive authority and may apply any such source with or without modification. Any action that may be brought under federal law or the law of the State of Wisconsin may be brought in tribal court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.307</num>
      <heading>Court Rules</heading>
      <text>The chief judge may prescribe, subject to amendment by the Tribal Governing Board, any rule necessary for the conduct of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court not inconsistent with the provisions of this Chapter.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.308</num>
      <heading>Application Of Tribal Code Of Law</heading>
      <text>This Chapter applies in all actions of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court, except where specific Titles of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code of Law (LCOTCL) provides for specific procedures in particular actions.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.309</num>
      <heading>Penalties And Forfeitures</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All penalties and forfeitures assessed shall be in accordance with the provisions set forth in Tribal Ordinances. No criminal penalty shall exceed the limitations contained in applicable federal law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All penalties and forfeitures collected shall be disposed of in a manner deemed appropriate by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.310</num>
      <heading>Indian Civil Rights Act</heading>
      <text>All proceedings in Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court shall be conducted in conformity with the Indian Civil Rights Act of 1968, 25 U.S.C. §§1301 – 1303.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.4</num>
    <heading>Judges And Magistrates</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.401</num>
      <heading>Selection Of Judges And Magistrates</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Governing Board shall appoint a Chief Judge, and may appoint such Associate Judges and Magistrates, upon such terms and conditions as are determined by the Tribal Governing Board. The judges and magistrates of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court shall be selected by a majority vote of the Tribal Governing Board at a meeting in which a quorum is present.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No person shall be eligible for selection as a judge or magistrate unless he or she is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is at least eighteen (18) years of age;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is of good moral character and integrity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has never been convicted of a felony;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has not been convicted within the last twelve (12) months of a misdemeanor or an ordinance adopting state criminal law;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Is capable of preparing opinions and orders and conducting hearings incident to the office of judge or magistrate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Has demonstrated knowledge of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law and understandings as necessary of applicable federal and state laws.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>No individual may serve as judge or magistrate while serving as a member of the Tribal Governing Board or as a tribal law enforcement officer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Governing Board may also select pro tempore judges as it deems advisable to perform any of the duties of the Tribal Judge.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.402</num>
      <heading>Terms Of Office</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each judge and magistrate shall hold office for a period of four (4) years, unless sooner removed for cause, or by reason of resignation, death or incapacity. A judge or magistrate shall be eligible for reappointment.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.403</num>
      <heading>Duties Of Judge</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A duly appointed Judge shall have the authority to act in all matters within the jurisdiction of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court or under the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law. A Tribal Court Judge shall have the authority to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Preside over all matters brought under the jurisdiction of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law and other matters under the jurisdiction of the Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Issue orders and judgement on all matters filed with the Tribal Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Exercise such other powers as set forth by the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.404</num>
      <heading>Duties Of Magistrate</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to the right of any party to seek a new ruling from the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court on any decision of a magistrate, a magistrate shall have the authority to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Issue orders related to service of summons by publication.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Preside over uncontested matters, and enter uncontested orders and judgments.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Preside at initial hearings (whether or not called by that particular name) in conservation, children's court, traffic, general conduct, and other matters where the function of the court proceeding is to conduct preliminary proceedings including but not limited to ascertaining the positions of parties, informing parties of their rights, and accepting pleas. The magistrate may also enter uncontested orders at such proceedings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Issue orders affecting discovery.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Issue subpoenas.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Issue search warrants.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Permit facsimile transmission filings in particular cases.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Issue orders related to the taking of testimony by telephone or audiovisual means.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Exercise such other powers as set forth by the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.405</num>
      <heading>Disqualification, Recusal, And Removal Of Judges Or Magistrates</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><u>Disqualification</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A judge or magistrate shall be disqualified to sit on any case in which he or she has any direct interest, is or has been or reasonably may be a witness, or is a spouse, parent, child, grandparent, grandchild, brother, or sister of a party. In the event that more than one judge has been appointed, the clerk of court shall randomly select from the Chief Judge, Associate Judge(s), Pro Tempore Judge(s), or the Magistrate to serve in the place of the disqualified judge or magistrate. In the event all Lac Courte Oreilles judges or magistrates are disqualified, the clerk of court shall randomly select from the list of appellate judges maintained under 2 LCOTCL Chapter 4 – Appellate Code to preside over the case.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An appellate judge shall be disqualified to hear any appeal in any case in which he or she sat as a trial judge, has any direct interest, has been a witness, or is a spouse, parent, child, grandparent, grandchild, brother, or sister of a party. Upon disqualification, the clerk of the appellate court shall randomly select another judge from the list of appellate judges to serve on the case.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><u>Recusal</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A judge or magistrate shall recuse himself or herself from a case in which he or she has a conflict of interest or the appearance of a conflict of interest or in any other case where failure to recuse would be a violation of 2 LCOTCL Chapter 6 – Judicial Conduct Code. In the event that more than one judge has been appointed, the clerk of court shall randomly select from the chief judge, associate judge(s), pro tempore judge(s), or the magistrate to serve in the place of the disqualified judge or magistrate. In the event all Lac Courte Oreilles judges or magistrates are disqualified, the clerk of court shall randomly select from the list of appellate judges maintained under 2 LCOTCL Chapter 4 – Appellate Code to preside over the case.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a Judge or Magistrate determines that he or she has no conflict of interest or the appearance of a conflict of interest in any case, a party may petition the Tribal Governing Board as to whether the Judge or Magistrate should be recused. The Tribal Governing Board shall make a decision on the Judge or Magistrate's recusal by a majority vote of a quorum of the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text><u>Removal of Judge or Magistrate</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A judge or magistrate may be suspended from office upon written charges brought for his or her removal which recited good cause. Good cause shall be limited to serious or repeated violations of 2 LCOTCL Chapter 6 – Judicial Conduct Code, a conviction of a crime or of an ordinance adopting a state criminal statute, a repeated failure to attend scheduled court dates, or serious or repeated disregard of unambiguous tribal laws. A hearing shall be provided before the Tribal Governing Board within ten (10) days of the judge's or magistrate's receipt of written notice of the charges, at which time the judge or magistrate shall be provided with the opportunity to respond to the charges against him or her, including the presentation of the testimony of witnesses in his or her behalf. A judge or magistrate may be removed only for good cause shown at the hearing, and only upon a majority vote taken by secret ballot of a quorum of the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon the removal, resignation, or physical or mental incapacity of a judge or magistrate, the Tribal Governing Board shall appoint an individual to the remainder of the term of office.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.406</num>
      <heading>Immunity Of Judges And Magistrates</heading>
      <text>Judges and magistrates shall be immune from civil liability arising from the true and faithful performance of his/her lawful acts and deeds while serving in the capacity of a judge or magistrate for the Tribal Court or for any other court of competent jurisdiction.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.407</num>
      <heading>Compensation</heading>
      <text>Judges and magistrates shall receive such compensation as established by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.5</num>
    <heading>Clerk Of Court</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.501</num>
      <heading>Appointment Of Clerk Of Court</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Governing shall appoint a Clerk of Court, and may appoint such deputy or assistant Clerks of Court, upon such terms and conditions as are determined by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.502</num>
      <heading>Duties Of Clerk Of Court</heading>
      <text>The Clerk shall render assistance to the Tribal Court, to tribal law enforcement personnel, and to all other persons having business with the Court. The Clerk shall serve as the Clerk of the Court of Appeals. The Clerk shall attend and keep written records of all proceedings of the Tribal Court, and is authorized to administer oaths and to collect fees, fines, forfeitures, costs and other monies. The Clerk and any deputy or assistant clerks shall be bonded in an amount fixed by the Tribal Governing Board, and shall transmit any and all monies received to the Tribal Secretary-Treasurer. The Clerk shall assure that a verbatim stenographic or electronic record is made of all proceedings of the Tribal Court. The Clerk may delegate any of the foregoing duties to the assistant clerk, while maintaining supervision and responsibility for the duty so delegated. The Clerk shall make periodic accountings to the Tribal Governing Board and to the Tribal Court of all funds received and disbursed by the Clerk. Such accounting shall be made at least annually, and upon request of either the Tribal Governing Board or Tribal Court.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.6</num>
    <heading>Attorney General / Prosecutor</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.601</num>
      <heading>Appointment Of Attorney General / Prosecutor</heading>
      <text>An Attorney General / Tribal Prosecutor shall be appointed by the Tribal Governing Board, for such term and upon such conditions as are determined by the Tribal Governing Board. The Tribal Governing Board may also appoint such deputy, assistant, special, or pro tempore Attorney General(s) / prosecutors as it deems advisable to perform any of the duties of the Tribal Prosecutor. The Attorney General / Tribal Prosecutor may also appoint such special or pro tempore prosecutors when advisable to perform any of the duties of the Tribal Prosecutor.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.602</num>
      <heading>Duties Of Attorney General / Prosecutor</heading>
      <text>The Attorney General / Tribal Prosecutor, or such designated deputy, assistant, special, or pro tempore Attorney General(s) / prosecutors as deemed advisable by the Attorney General to perform any of the duties of the Tribal Prosecutor, shall represent the Tribe before the Tribal Court in all appropriate proceedings and may bring any action to enforce the Tribal Code of Law and any other tribal ordinance, which shall be brought in the name of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians or in the name of any of the Tribe's entities</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.7</num>
    <heading>Court Files</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.701</num>
      <heading>Court Files To Be Open</heading>
      <text>Except as specified herein, all records and files of the Tribal Court shall be available for public inspection during the regular business hours of the Tribal Court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.702</num>
      <heading>Closed Files</heading>
      <text>All juvenile and domestic relations files, and all other files specified by the Tribal Code of Law, shall be closed. The court may in its discretion and in the interest of privacy, deem other court files as closed files. All closed files shall be unavailable for public inspection without an order of the Tribal Court. This section shall not be construed to prevent law enforcement personnel or other Tribal entities/departments as otherwise authorized by law, from inspecting files of the Tribal Court upon request.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.703</num>
      <heading>Control Of Court Files</heading>
      <text>No court files may be removed from the custody, control, and physical possession of the Tribal Court. Individuals securing copies of documents from Tribal Court files or transcripts of Tribal Court proceedings, shall, unless otherwise authorized by law or ordered by the Tribal Court, pay the actual costs of reproduction of such material.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.8</num>
    <heading>Practice Before The Court</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.801</num>
      <heading>Right To Counsel</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any party appearing before the Tribal Court has the right to be represented by an attorney or lay advocate at the party's expense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any person who is a party in any action or proceedings before the Tribal Court may represent herself or himself, or be represented by any other person who is licensed to appear before the Tribal Court, except the Clerk of Court, the Deputy Clerk, a Judge or Magistrate of the Tribal Court, a current member of the Tribal Governing Board, or a tribal law enforcement officer.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.802</num>
      <heading>Admission To Practice Required</heading>
      <text>No attorney or lay advocate shall represent any person in an action before the Tribal Court unless such attorney or lay advocate is duly admitted to practice before the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court. The Tribal Court may grant leave to appear in a single case to any individual who is a member in good standing of another state or tribal bar.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.803</num>
      <heading>Procedure For Admission</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An attorney for the purposes of this subchapter shall be a person who has graduated from an American Bar Association accredited institution and has been admitted to a court or jurisdiction. A Lay Advocate is a person who has completed certified training in the practice of law in tribal courts.  A Lay advocate cannot be an attorney who is inactive or is not in current standing in another jurisdiction. Any person wishing to practice before the Tribal Court shall file a written request for admission with the Clerk of Court, accompanied by a Certificate of Good Standing from the State Bar or Supreme Court of the State in which such attorney is duly licensed to practice law. Such request shall be accompanied by an admission fee as determined by the Court rule pursuant to subs. (2)(a), below.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Attorneys may appear on behalf of any party in any action or proceeding before the Tribal Court, provided they are licensed to practice law before the Tribal Court.  Such license shall be issued upon compliance with the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Filing with the Clerk of Court an affidavit that the applicant is licensed to practice law and provides evidence that the attorney is in good standing before the highest court of any state; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Filing with the Clerk of Court an affidavit that the applicant has studied and is familiar with the Constitution and By-Laws of the Tribe, this Code, the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law (LCOTCL), Title 25 of the United States Code and Title 25 of the Code of Federal Regulations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Paying an annual license fee of one hundred dollars ($100.00); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Taking the following oath before the Clerk of Court, either in person or by affidavit:</text>
          <text>"I do solemnly swear (or affirm) that I will support the laws of the Lac Courte 			Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians;</text>
          <text>I will maintain the respect due to the Tribal Court and its judicial officers;</text>
          <text>I will not counsel or maintain any suit or proceeding which shall appear to me 			unjust, nor any defense except such as I believe to be honestly valid or debatable 			under the law;</text>
          <text>I will employ confidentiality for the purpose of maintaining the causes confided to 		me, and such means only as are consistent with truth and honor, and I will never 			seek to mislead any judge or magistrate, or by false statement or 					misrepresentation of fact or law;</text>
          <text>I will employ in the conduct of my duties the highest degree of ethics and moral 			standards with which my profession is charged, and I will be guided at all times 			by the quest for truth and justice;</text>
          <text>In the conduct of my duties as an attorney, I will not impugn the morals, 				character, honesty, good faith, or competence of any person, nor advance any fact 			prejudicial to the honor or reputation of any person, unless required by the justice 			of the cause with which I am charged."</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any lay advocate wishing to practice before the Tribal Court shall file a written request for admission with the Clerk of Court, accompanied by an affidavit reciting the qualification of such spokesman to represent another before the Court.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Filing an affidavit with the Clerk of Court which states that the applicant has studied and is familiar with Constitution and By-Laws of the Tribe, this Code, the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law (LCOTCL), Title 25 of the United States Code and Title 25 of the Code of Federal Regulations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Paying an annual license fee of $50; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Taking the following oath before the Clerk of Court either in person or by affidavit:</text>
          <text>"I do solemnly swear (or affirm) that I will support all laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians;</text>
          <text>I will maintain the respect due to the Tribal Court and its judicial officers; and</text>
          <text>I will employ confidentiality for the purposes of maintaining the causes confided 			to me, and such means only as are consistent with truth and honor, and I will 			never seek to mislead any judge, justice, jury or elder by any artifice, or by false 			statement or misrepresentation of fact or law; and</text>
          <text>I will conduct myself in an orderly, courteous and respectful manner and shall not misbehave or disrupt, obstruct, or otherwise interfere with the conduct of any proceeding by the Court or the administration of justice by the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court."</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Upon the successful determination of admission to the practice an attorney shall be issued a bar number which shall be required on all documents submitted to the Tribal Court.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Attorneys shall be number LCO1001;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Lay advocates shall be numbered LCOA1001; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attorneys admitted Pro Hac Vice shall be numbered LCOT1001.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.804</num>
      <heading>Revocation Of License To Practice Before The Court</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any license issued pursuant to §1.802 and §1.803 of this Chapter may be revoked or suspended by the Tribal Court.  Such action may be taken on its own motion or upon sworn complaint by a citizen of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any license may be revoked or suspended by the Tribal Court upon a finding that the licensee has been disbarred or suspended from the practice of law by any court of the United States, State, or Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any license may be revoked or suspended by the Tribal Court upon a finding that a attorney or lay advocate has filed a false affidavit with the Clerk of Court to obtain her/his license, or has violated her/his oath made before the Clerk of Court or has engaged in misconduct or unethical conduct as an attorney or lay advocate which has violated her/his oath.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.805</num>
      <heading>Procedure For Revocation Of License To Practice Before The Court</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Court shall provide a written notice of revocation or suspension to the licensee of the motion or complaint and a right to a hearing before a judge of the Tribal Court. The Licensee shall have ten (10) days to respond to the notice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A hearing shall be conducted, within thirty days of the notice under section (1), before a judge of the Tribal Court.  The Hearing will be informal and the Licensee shall be afforded the opportunity to respond to the complaint or the motion. The hearing will be final.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Following a hearing, the Tribal Court may revoke, suspend, or sanction, a license as deemed appropriate based in the information provided at the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.806</num>
      <heading>Admissions And Continuation Rules</heading>
      <text>The chief judge may, by rule, impose requirements in addition to those listed in § 1.803 for admission to the bar and for continuation of membership in the bar, which may include education requirements, examination requirements, renewal fees, or any combination thereof.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.9</num>
    <heading>Starting An Action</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.901</num>
      <heading>Summons And Complaint</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An action in Tribal Court is commenced by the filing of a summons and complaint as prescribed by this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The summons and complaint shall be a single document setting forth the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The names and addresses, and tribal status of the parties. If a party who is not a member of the Tribe is alleged to be eligible for membership in the Tribe, the complaint shall be accompanied by an original certificate of eligibility from the Tribe's enrollment office or enrollment committee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The case number assigned by the Clerk of Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A command to the defendant to appear at tribal court at a date, time and place specified by the Clerk of Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A brief statement, including approximate date and place, of the transaction or occurrence giving rise to the action.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The relief requested.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A statement that failure to appear may result in a judgment taken against the defendant for the relief requested, plus costs and attorney fees.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The dated signature of the Clerk of Court and of the plaintiff or plaintiff's attorney or lay advocate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Clerk of Court shall make available forms of the summons and complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The first appearance date specified under subs. (2)(c), above shall be no less than 20 days and no more than 60 days from the date of issuance of the summons and complaint. Service, if by mail, shall be made no less than ten days prior to the first appearance date. Service, if personal, shall be made no less than seven days prior to the first appearance date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Clerk of Court shall not accept for filing any summons and complaint that does not bear the dated signature of the plaintiff or plaintiff's attorney, or that is not accompanied by the filing fee as required by § 1.1501 (1) and, if applicable, the mailing fee as required by § 1.1501 (2).</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.902</num>
      <heading>Service Of The Summons And Complaint</heading>
      <text>Service of the summons and complaint may be by the following methods:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><u>Natural Person</u>. The plaintiff may cause personal service to be made upon the defendant by hand delivery to the defendant in person or to any person of apparent normal understanding no less than 16 years old residing within the residence of the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><u>Natural Person under Disability</u>. When the defendant is a minor under the age of 18 years, service shall be made upon the minor's parent or guardian. When a minor defendant is 14 years of age or over, service shall also be made on the minor. When the defendant is an adult who is known by the plaintiff to have a guardian, service shall be made on the defendant and on the defendant's guardian. Service may be made personally as provided in subs. (1) above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text><u>Service on Tribe</u>. When the defendant is the Tribe, service may be made by delivering a copy of the summons and complaint to the Chairman, Vice-Chairman, or Secretary-Treasurer of the Tribe, or the Attorney General or the Chairman's administrative assistant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text><u>Service on other Governmental Bodies</u>. When the defendant is a governmental body other than the Tribe, service shall be made on the agent of the governmental body as designated under the law of the State in which service is made; however, service may be made either personally or by certified mail as provided in this section. If service is made personally, it may be made upon the agent so designated or upon the person apparently in charge of the agent's office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text><u>Service on Domestic or Foreign Corporations or Limited Liability Companies</u>. When the defendant is a domestic or foreign corporation or limited liability company, service shall be made on the agent of the domestic or foreign corporation or limited liability company as designated under the law of the State in which service is made; however, service may be made either personally or by certified mail as provided in this section. If service is made personally, it may be made upon the agent so designated or upon the person apparently in charge of the agent's office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text><u>Service by Certified Mail</u>. A plaintiff may request the Clerk of Court to make service by certified mail, in which case the Clerk of Court shall mail a copy of the summons and complaint to each defendant, other individual, or agents as designated according to defendant's status under subs. (1) - (5), above. Mail shall be certified, return receipt requested, return requested if not claimed within five days. The Clerk shall charge the plaintiff the fees as required by § 1.1501 of this ordinance for service by certified mail, receipt requested, return postage guaranteed. Service by mail shall be complete upon mailing unless the envelope enclosing the summons and complaint is returned unopened by the post office to the Clerk of Court prior to the date of the first appearance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text><u>Service by Publication</u>. If service cannot reasonably be made under subs. (1) - (6) of this ordinance, service by publication may be made. Plaintiff shall cause a summons to be published in a newspaper of general circulation in the area of the defendant's last known residence. The summons for publication shall inform the defendant that a lawsuit has been filed against the defendant in Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court, and shall give the names of the parties, the case number, and the address of the Clerk of Court, with the advice that a copy of the full summons and complaint may be obtained at that address. Publication shall occur once each week for three consecutive weeks. The plaintiff shall file an affidavit showing the required publication and an affidavit detailing attempts to personally serve the defendant and to serve the defendant by mail and the reasons why such attempts failed and why the plaintiff does not believe additional attempts will be successful.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text><u>Who May Serve</u>. Any person over eighteen years of age, not a party to the action, may make personal service. In the case of personal service, an affidavit of service shall be returned to the Clerk of Court and shall constitute proof of service. If service is disputed, the person making personal service may be required to testify as to the circumstances of the service.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.903</num>
      <heading>Answers, Counterclaims, Cross-Complaints, And Third-Party Complaints</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All parties shall appear on the first appearance date specified in the summons and complaint. All answers, counterclaims and cross complaints may be made orally or in writing. If made in writing, any such pleadings shall be filed with the Clerk of Court with copies served on all parties. A third-party complaint must be made in writing and shall be filed with the Clerk of Court and served on the third-party defendant on or before the return date or at such later date as the Court allows.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Written pleadings shall not substitute for personal appearance or appearance by an attorney or lay advocate on the first appearance date. Failure of any party to appear may result in judgment as provided in §§ 1.1101 and 1.1102 of this ordinance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon the first appearance date, the court shall determine whether the defendant wishes to make a defense to the complaint. If the defendant does not wish to make a defense or raise a counterclaim, judgment may be entered in favor of the plaintiff. If the defendant does wish to make a defense, the court shall determine whether the parties wish to settle their differences without trial. If such settlement is made, the court shall enter judgment, or dismiss the complaint, as called for by the settlement. If the parties do not make such a settlement, a trial date shall be set or a scheduling order under § 1.905 of this ordinance, shall be entered depending on the complexity of the case. Trial may be had on the date of the first appearance if all parties and the court consent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any party may request a substitution of judge for cause by making such request at the hearing on the first appearance date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The court may in its discretion adjourn the first appearance as the interests of justice require.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.904</num>
      <heading>Filing And Service Of Papers After Summons And Complaint</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The service of any papers in an action subsequent to the summons and complaint may be made by first-class mail or facsimile transmission, or electronic mail to the party and to the party's attorney or lay advocate who has filed a notice of appearance in the action, or by delivery to such person, the person's home, or the person's office. No filing may be made by electronic facsimile (fax) unless permitted by specific order of a judge or magistrate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No party shall file any paper in an action without also serving a copy on every other party in the action, except for a party in default.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No pleading, motion, or other paper may be filed to harass or cause unnecessary delay or needless increase in expense, or that is not well-grounded in fact and warranted by existing law, or by a good faith argument for the extension, modification, or reversal of existing law. The court may impose sanctions, including a requirement that any party, attorney, or lay advocate who makes any such filing pay reasonable attorney fees to the other party, dismissal of a complaint or petition, or any other remedy fashioned by the Court.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.905</num>
      <heading>Scheduling Order</heading>
      <text>On or after the first appearance date, the Court may enter a scheduling order, and may from time to time thereafter amend the order. The entry of any scheduling order shall occur after a scheduling conference which may be held either as part of the first appearance or as a separate scheduling conference. At any such conference, any unrepresented party must appear in person, and at least one attorney or lay advocate must appear for any party who has such representation. After consultation the court shall issue a scheduling order including such of the following as are applicable to the circumstances and complexity of the case:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The time within which any other parties shall be joined;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The time within which any motions shall be filed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The time within which any pleadings may be amended;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The time within which motion for default judgment may be heard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The methods and timetables for the completion of discovery;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The time within which motion for summary judgment may be heard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The date for a pretrial conference;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The date for trial; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other matters governing the conduct of the case that the court deems appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.906</num>
      <heading>Status Conferences</heading>
      <text>The court may on its own motion or upon a request of a party set a status conference whenever useful to the advancement of a case.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.907</num>
      <heading>Pre-Trial Discovery</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The methods and timetables for pre-trial discovery shall be set by the Court in a scheduling order. Discovery shall be tailored to allow adequate case assessment and trial preparation, but shall not be permitted to harass or oppress a party, to unreasonably increase expense, or to waste time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A party seeking discovery who has not served a proper demand as permitted by a scheduling order and whose demand has not been timely met by another party, may seek an order compelling the other party to comply with the demand and may be awarded its costs and fees necessitated by the failure to comply, and other relief as the Court deems appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A party who has received a discovery demand that is not authorized by a scheduling order of that is otherwise improper may seek a protective order against the demand and may be awarded its costs and fees necessitated by discovery demand, and other relief as the Court deems appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.908</num>
      <heading>Telephone And Audiovisual Proceedings</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On its own motion or motion of any party the Court may conduct any proceeding by telephone or audiovisual means. Any party seeking to appear in person or by counsel by telephone or audiovisual means shall secure the consent of the Court. Any party may object to such appearance, and the Court shall then determine if such appearance shall be allowed. Any party wishing to present evidence by telephone or audiovisual means shall either secure the consent of the other party or provide notice to the other party that unless objection is received within the time set by the court the court may receive such evidence by telephone or audiovisual means.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In determining whether to conduct a proceeding, allow an appearance, or allow evidence to be presented by telephone or audiovisual means the court shall consider the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whether all parties have requested or consented to such procedure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The availability of adequate equipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whether any undue surprise or prejudice would result;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Whether there is good reason for the individual appearing by telephone or audiovisual means not to be physically present in court;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The convenience and expense to the court, parties, and witnesses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Whether the appearance of a witness by telephone or audiovisual means will allow full and effective cross-examination and access to relevant documents and other exhibits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The importance of presenting the testimony of a witness in open court, in order to observe demeanor, or in order to maintain the solemnity of proceedings and impress on the witness the duty to testify truthfully;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Where the judge is participating by telephone or audiovisual means, the above factors as applicable, and the cost/benefit comparison of proceeding by telephone or audiovisual means or otherwise; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Any other factor the court deems relevant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If testimony is offered by telephone or audiovisual means, the proceedings shall be simultaneously recorded either by stenographic or electronic means. Any proceeding required to be conducted in open court shall be conducted in such a way that any interested observers may hear the proceedings.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.909</num>
      <heading>Time</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In computing any period of time prescribed or allowed by this Tribal Code of Law, or any other ordinance or statute, or by order of the court, the day of the act, event, or default from which the designated time period begins to run shall not be included. The last day of the period shall be included unless it is a day that the clerk of court's office is closed, in which case the period shall extend until the day that the clerk of court's office is open next. When the period of time prescribed or allowed is ten days or less, Saturdays and Sundays are excluded in the computation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When an act is required to be done at or within a specified time, the court may order the period enlarged on motion for cause and upon just terms. No motion filed after the expiration of the specified time shall be granted unless excusable neglect is shown.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A written motion, other than one which may be heard ex parte, shall be served with notice of hearing on the motion not later than five days before the hearing unless a shorter time is provided by ordinance or order of the court. A shortened time may be sought for cause by ex parte motion and affidavit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whenever a party has a right or is required to do some act or take some proceedings within a prescribed period of time after the service of a notice or other paper on the party, the party shall have three additional days if the notice or paper is served by mail or reputable express carrier, or one additional day if the notice or paper is served by facsimile transmission completed by 4:00 p.m. and midnight.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.910</num>
      <heading>Subpoenas</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The judges or magistrates of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court shall have the power to issue subpoenas for the attendance of witnesses and production of documents or physical evidence on the request of any party to a case or on the court's own motion, which subpoena shall bear the signature of the judge or magistrate issuing it. Service of subpoena shall be by law enforcement personnel or by an individual appointed by the court for that purpose, and may be by any means directed by the court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Service of a subpoena unless otherwise directed by the court shall be made by delivering a copy of it to the person named or by leaving a copy at the person's place of residence with any competent person sixteen (16) years or older who also resides there.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Proof of service of the subpoena shall be filed with the Clerk of Court by noting on the back of a copy of the subpoena the date, time and place what tit was served, and noting the name of the person to whom it was delivered. Proof of service shall be signed by the person who actually served the subpoena. The court may in its discretion provide for alternative reliable proof of service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In the absence of justification satisfactory to the court, a person who fails to obey a subpoena may be deemed to be in contempt of court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Each witness answering a subpoena shall be entitled to a witness fee of $25 per day. The party requesting the subpoena shall deposit the fee with the Clerk of Court at the time of the request. The Clerk of Court shall pay the witness fee to the witness after the witness testifies or is excused from further testimony by the Court and shall return the fee to the party requesting the subpoena if for any reason the witness does not appear as subpoenaed. The witness fee may be included in an award of costs to a prevailing party.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.911</num>
      <heading>Statute Of Limitations</heading>
      <text>Unless a specific limitation on an action is provided by tribal ordinance, and contract claim may be presented within six years of the accrual of the claim, and tort claim other than a professional malpractice may be presented within three years of the accrual of the claim, and any professional malpractice claim may be presented within three years of the discovery of the claim. The filing in federal or state court or any action which should properly be brought in Tribal Court tolls the limitation.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.10</num>
    <heading>Trial</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1001</num>
      <heading>Trial To Court</heading>
      <text>All trials in Tribal Court shall be to the Court without a jury.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1002</num>
      <heading>Formality</heading>
      <text>Trials shall be conducted by the Court with the degree of formality necessitated by the circumstances. Circumstances which the court may consider in determining the degree of formality to be used include the number of parties, the complexity of the case, the representation or lack thereof of the parties, and such other factors as the Court deems appropriate. In all cases, each party shall be allowed to present evidence and argument and to examine witnesses to the extent deemed appropriate by the Court for full disclosure of the pertinent facts.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1003</num>
      <heading>Evidence</heading>
      <text>Evidence shall be admitted as provided in the Lac Courte Oreilles Rules of Evidence. In cases where circumstances warrant, the court may waive the 2 LCOTCL Chapter 3 –Rules of Evidence, or particular provisions, or other particular application thereof, except those related to privilege pursuant to 2 LCOTCL Chapter 3 –Rules of Evidence. An essential finding of fact may not be based on hearsay unless it would be admissible pursuant to 2 LCOTCL Chapter 3 –Rules of Evidence.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1004</num>
      <heading>Court Control</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The judge shall establish the order of proof and argument consistent with fair and prompt resolution of the dispute.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The judge may question witnesses.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1005</num>
      <heading>Burden Of Proof</heading>
      <text>Where none is otherwise stated, the burden of proof shall be on the party asserting a claim or affirmative defense to prove each element of the claim or affirmative defense by a preponderance of the evidence.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.11</num>
    <heading>Judgment</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1101</num>
      <heading>Failure Of Plaintiff To Appear</heading>
      <text>If the plaintiff fails to appear at the first appearance or for trial, the court may dismiss the complaint. Dismissal shall be without prejudice unless a complaint filed by the plaintiff arising from the same transaction or occurrence has been dismissed on the same grounds once before.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1102</num>
      <heading>Failure Of Defendant To Appear</heading>
      <text>If the defendant fails to appear at the first appearance or at trial, the court may enter judgment for plaintiff upon due proof of facts which show the plaintiff is entitled to judgment.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1103</num>
      <heading>Summary Judgment</heading>
      <text>At any time not barred by a scheduling order in the case, a party may move for summary judgment on any claim, counterclaim, cross-claim or third-party claim, which shall be granted if the pleadings, depositions, answers to interrogatories, admissions, and evidentiary affidavits on file show that there is no genuine issue as to any material fact and that the moving or opposing party is entitled to judgment as a matter of law. The court may, in its discretion, hold a non-evidentiary hearing on the motion. Any material upon which the motion is based which is not on file at the time of the filing of the motion shall be filed with the motion. Any counter affidavits or other material in opposition to the motion shall be filed and served within the time set by scheduling order, or if none is in effect, no more than 21 days after service of the motion and supporting papers on the responding party. If the court holds a hearing on the motion, it shall be no sooner than five days after the last date allowed for filing responsive materials. Interlocutory summary judgment may be entered on some but not all claims or issues in a case. The court may enter summary judgment in favor of a party even though the party has not moved for summary judgment, if the materials submitted in support of and opposition to another party's motion for summary judgment show that summary judgment is appropriate under the standards set by this section.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1104</num>
      <heading>Judgment After Trial</heading>
      <text>After trial, the court may give its decision orally immediately, or it may file written findings of fact, conclusions of law, and judgment, no later than 45 days following trial.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1105</num>
      <heading>Reopening Judgment</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Judgment may be reopened at any time within one year of judgment in any case where service was by mail or publication, the defendant did not receive actual notice of the action and did not appear in the action or otherwise submit to the jurisdiction of the court, and the defendant petitions the court to reopen the judgment within 15 days of receiving actual notice of the action or judgment. Such petition shall be verified and shall state the facts upon which the petitioner bases the claim to reopen under this subparagraph. After hearing, the court may grant the petition to reopen, in which case a trial date shall be set.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Default judgment may be reopened on all grounds other than failure of actual notice, by petition for good cause shown within six months of entry of judgment.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1106</num>
      <heading>Costs</heading>
      <text>The court, in its discretion, may assess costs against a defendant found guilty of violating a tribal ordinance, and may, in its discretion, apportion and assess costs against the respective parties to a civil action. Such costs shall not include attorney fees, except as specifically provided by ordinance. Such costs shall be included in the judgment.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1107</num>
      <heading>Disclosure Of Assets</heading>
      <text>When a judgment for money damages is entered under this chapter, the court shall order that the judgment debtor execute, under penalty of contempt, within 15 days of the entry of judgment unless the judgment is satisfied sooner, a statement, on forms provided by the Clerk of Court, disclosing, as of the date of judgment, the debtor's name, residence address, employers and their addresses, frequency of pay periods and gross and net pay per period, any non-USA trust real property interests, cash on hand, financial institutions in which the debtor has any funds and the amount of funds in each institution, the names and addresses of all persons who hold any property belonging to the debtor or who owe any money or property to the debtor, and all items and property worth more than $100.00.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1108</num>
      <heading>Effect Of Judgment</heading>
      <text>Entry of a judgment entitles the prevailing party to enforcement by the Tribal Court on its terms. A judgment for a sum certain may be enforced by writ of execution against property of the losing party which is located on the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1109</num>
      <heading>Installment Payments</heading>
      <text>Upon the request of the party against whom judgment is entered, which can be made orally at the time of the hearing or by petition, and after such inquiry as the judge deems proper, the judge may order the payment of such judgment by installments, in such amounts and such times as the judge deems just and reasonable. Such order shall also provide for a stay of further proceedings to collect the judgment during said party's compliance with the order.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1110</num>
      <heading>Effect Of Appeal On Judgment</heading>
      <text>The filing of an appeal with the Lac Courte Oreilles Court of Appeals, pursuant to the requirements of 2 LCOTCL Chapter 4 – Appellate Code, shall not prevent the enforcement of the judgment of the trial court, unless the trial court on its own motion or that of a party orders a stay of enforcement pending the appeal.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.12</num>
    <heading>Enforcement Of Judgment</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1201</num>
      <heading>Power Of The Court</heading>
      <text>Upon entry of judgment the Tribal Court may upon application of the prevailing party:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue a writ of execution which shall command tribal enforcement personnel to collect the amount of the judgment from the losing party;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Issue a writ of execution which shall command any natural or legal person, partnership, or limited liability entity, or the tribe to pay over to the prevailing party any asset or income held by any such person, partnership, entity or the tribe that is owned by or which may accrue to the benefit of the losing party, provided that no such writ shall run against tribal assets or income without the consent of the tribe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Issue a subpoena to the losing party, ordering the party to appear before the Court at a time and place specified, and to testify under oath concerning property, or any debts due or to become due to him, place of employment, name of employer, and the amount of wages received, and other pertinent matters that would enable the prevailing party to collect the judgment.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1202</num>
      <heading>Writ Of Execution</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the writ of execution, tribal law enforcement personnel shall serve the writ upon the losing party and take possession of any non-exempt property as ordered by the Tribal Court. Within 30 days, the tribal law enforcement personnel shall cause a sale of such property. The proceeds of the sale shall be returned to the Tribal Court within 30 days above prescribed. The net proceeds of such sale, after deducting sale expenses and amounts due any secured party under subs. (2), below shall be remitted to the prevailing party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If there exists a perfected security interest in the sold property, there shall be deducted from the proceeds of sale the amount due under the security agreement, and such amount shall be paid to the secured party. In the event a sufficient amount does not remain to satisfy the total amount due under the security agreement, after deducting other sale expenses any amount remaining shall be paid over to the secured party.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1203</num>
      <heading>Stay Of Writ</heading>
      <text>The losing party may prevent the issuance of a writ of execution or judicial sale, by presenting to the Tribal Court sufficient proof that said party has made payment of the judgment to the prevailing party, or is willing to commence payment of the judgment to the prevailing party, upon terms acceptable to the prevailing party and the Court. Upon such proof, the Tribal Court shall not issue a writ of execution, and, if one has been issued, shall rescind the order.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1204</num>
      <heading>Property Exempt From Execution</heading>
      <text>The following property shall be exempt from levy and sale under any execution:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All interests in property held in trust by the United States.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All assets and income of the Tribe, unless specifically pledged.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All personal consumer goods, clothing, furniture, utensils, books and appliances, and the like, kept for the personal use of the debtor or the debtor's dependents, not exceeding $5,000 in value.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The tools, implements, materials, stock, apparatus, or other things needed by the judgment debtor to carry on his profession, trade, occupation, or business in which he is principally engaged, not exceeding $7,500 in value.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A dwelling and home appurtenances thereto, owned in fee and occupied by the judgment debtor, not exceeding $40,000 in value excepting mortgage, construction, and tax liens.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>All other exempt property.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1205</num>
      <heading>Interest On Judgments</heading>
      <text>Any judgment not paid within the time prescribed by the court, or if no time is prescribed, within 30 days of the date of judgment, shall accrue simple interest on the balance not paid at the rate of 1.5% per month. The filing of an appeal shall not stop the accrual of interest.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.13</num>
    <heading>Foreign Judgments</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1301</num>
      <heading>Definition</heading>
      <text>In this chapter "foreign judgment" means any judgment, decree, or order of a court of the United States or of any other court which is entitled to full faith and credit in the tribal court. "Judgment debtor" means any person against whom a judgment was entered in any court, and against whom enforcement is sought in Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1302</num>
      <heading>Filing And Status Of Foreign Judgments</heading>
      <text>A certified copy of any foreign judgment may be filed with the clerk of court. The clerk of court shall treat the foreign judgment in the same manner as the judgment of the tribal court. A judgment so filed has the same effect and is subject to the same procedures and status as a judgment of tribal court, and may be enforced or satisfied in like manner, except that the Tribal Court shall, after notice and hearing upon its own motion or motion of a party, have the right to review and modify any foreign order for the enforcement of a judgment, including but not limited to garnishment orders.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1303</num>
      <heading>Notice Of Filing</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the time of filing of the foreign judgment, the judgment creditor or lawyer shall make and file with the clerk of court an affidavit setting forth the name and last-known post office address of the judgment debtor, the judgment debtor's lawyer, if any, the judgment creditor, and the judgment creditor's lawyer, if any.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Promptly upon filing of the foreign judgment and affidavit, the clerk shall mail notice of the filing to the judgment debtor and the judgment debtor's lawyer as named in the affidavit, and shall record proof of such mailing in the file. The notice shall include the name and address of the judgment creditor and the judgment creditor's lawyer, if any. The judgment creditor may also mail such notice and file proof of such mailing with the clerk of court. Failure of either the clerk or the judgment creditor to mail notice as provided in this section shall not affect the enforceability of the foreign judgment if proof of mailing by the other is filed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No execution or other process for enforcement of a foreign judgment shall issue until 15 days after the foreign judgment is filed.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1304</num>
      <heading>Stay</heading>
      <text>If the judgment debtor shows the court that an appeal from the foreign judgment is pending or will be taken, or that a stay of execution has been granted, the court or magistrate shall stay enforcement of the foreign judgment until the appeal is concluded, the time for appeal expires, or the stay of execution expires or is vacated, upon proof that the judgment debtor has furnished security for the satisfaction of the judgment as required by the court in which the judgment was rendered, or if no such security was required, upon furnishing security in an amount and kind satisfactory to the tribal court.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.14</num>
    <heading>Contempt Of Court</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1401</num>
      <heading>Definition</heading>
      <text>Contempt of court means any of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Misconduct in the presence of the court which interferes with a court proceeding or with the administration of justice, or which impairs respect for the court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disobedience, resistance, or obstruction of the authority, process, order, or judgment of the court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refusal as a witness to appear, be sworn, or answer a question.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Refusal to produce a record, document, or other object.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Refusal or failure as a party or, in a children's court case, of an affected person, to obey an order to appear.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1402</num>
      <heading>Power Of Court To Punish Contempt Of Court</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Court may impose a sanction for contempt of court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1403</num>
      <heading>Summary Procedure</heading>
      <text>The judge presiding in an action or proceeding may impose a sanction upon a person who commits a contempt of court in the actual presence of the court. The judge shall impose the sanction immediately after the contempt of court and only for the purpose of preserving order in the court and preserving the authority and dignity of the court. A violation of § 1.1401 (3) or (5) may be considered under this section even though the contemnor does not appear in court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1404</num>
      <heading>Nonsummary Procedure</heading>
      <text>A person aggrieved by a contempt of court may seek imposition of a sanction for the contempt by filing a motion for that purpose in the proceeding to which the contempt is related. The court, after notice and hearing, may impose a sanction.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1405</num>
      <heading>Sanctions Authorized</heading>
      <text>The court may impose one or more of the following sanctions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Payment of a sum of money sufficient to compensate for a loss or injury suffered by the party as a result of the contempt of court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A forfeiture not to exceed $5,000 for each instance of contempt, not to exceed $5,000 for all instances, occurring in one calendar day or for each calendar day the contempt of court continues.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An order designed to insure compliance with a prior order of the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Expulsion from Tribal Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Execution of a capias warrant for failing to appear to a court order to appear in person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Jailing for no more than five days for each instance of contempt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An award of costs and attorney fees occasioned by the contempt of court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A sanction other than the sanctions specified in subs. (1) - (7) of this ordinance, if the court specifically finds that those sanctions would be ineffectual to terminate a continuing contempt of court.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1406</num>
      <heading>Enforcement Of Monetary Sanctions</heading>
      <text>Any sanction imposed under § 1.1405 (1), (2), or (7) may be enforced by the court or aggrieved party by any procedure provided in § 1.1201 - § 1.1205. As part of the contempt proceeding the court may of its own motion or on motion of any party order any monetary sanction under § 1.1405 (1), (2), or (7), and the costs of incarceration under § 1.1405 (6) to be paid from any funds held by the Tribe, or which may in the future be held by the Tribe, for the individual who is the subject of the order, and any such order for payment shall have priority over any other disbursement of such funds.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1407</num>
      <heading>Defenses</heading>
      <text>The good faith protection of the alleged contemnor, or of a child, or of any other third party whom the alleged contemnor is privileged to defend, from imminent physical harm or the threat of imminent physical harm is an affirmative defense to an allegation of contempt.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.15</num>
    <heading>Fees And Costs</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1501</num>
      <heading>Collection Of Fees</heading>
      <text>The Court shall set, and the Clerk of Court shall collect fees for the services of the Court, including but not limited to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Filing of summons and complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Service of summons and complaint by mail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Filing of foreign judgment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Issuance of writ of execution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Provision of copies, and provision of certified copies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Provision of transcripts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Bar admission fees.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>1.16</num>
    <heading>Protection Of Court, Law Enforcement And Social Services Personnel</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1601</num>
      <heading>Violation</heading>
      <text>Any person who harasses, or threatens bodily harm to, any judge, magistrate or other court personnel, advocate, attorney, law enforcement, or social services personnel with the intent or effect of discouraging that person from discharging his or her duties under any ordinance of the tribe or rendering assistance to anyone seeking protection of rights under any ordinance of the Tribe may be prosecuted by the Tribe for violation of this section and shall be subject to a civil forfeiture not to exceed $5,000 for each violation.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1602</num>
      <heading>Definition</heading>
      <text>"Harassment" means, for purposes of this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Striking, shoving, kicking, or otherwise subjecting another to physical contact, or attempting or threatening to do the same, or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Engaging in a course of conduct or committing at least two acts which harass or intimidate another person and which serve no legitimate purpose.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1603</num>
      <heading>Intent</heading>
      <text>Intent may be determined by the circumstance surrounding the acts forming the basis of the alleged violation.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.1604</num>
      <heading>Prosecution</heading>
      <text>Any person who believes that he or she has been the victim of a violation of § 1.1601 may report such alleged violation to the office of the tribal prosecutor for a determination of whether the alleged violation shall be prosecuted. All actions under this section shall be brought by the Tribe in the name of the Tribe, and all forfeitures awarded shall be awarded to the Tribe.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
