<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>III-4</num>
  <heading>Lac Courte Oreilles Head Start/Early Head Start Policy Council By-Laws Of The Lac Courte Oreilles Band Of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</heading>
  <text class="center"><strong>Preamble</strong></text>
  <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians relating to the delivery of educational services which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, Article V, §§ 1(l) and (m) of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a housing authority, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the reservation" Article V, § 1 (l);  and "delegate to subordinate boards, officers, committees or cooperative associations which are open to all members of the Band any of the foregoing powers, reserving the right to review any action taken by virtue of such delegated powers" Article V, § 1 (m). This ordinance establishes that the purpose of the Lac Courte Oreilles Ojibwe Early Head Start ("Early Head Start") program is to provide students a comprehensive, bilingual and multicultural community-based education that nurtures theirs intellectual, spiritual, physical, emotional, mental and social development.</text>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>4.1</num>
    <heading>Introduction</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.101</num>
      <heading>Title</heading>
      <text>This ordinance shall be known as the Lac Courte Oreilles Head Start/Early Head Start Policy Council By-Laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.102</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians relating to the delivery of educational services which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, Article V, §§ 1(l) and (m) of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a housing authority, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the reservation" Article V, § 1 (l);  and "delegate to subordinate boards, officers, committees or cooperative associations which are open to all members of the Band any of the foregoing powers, reserving the right to review any action taken by virtue of such delegated powers" Article V, § 1 (m).</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.103</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>This ordinance establishes that the purpose of the Lac Courte Oreilles Ojibwe Early Head Start ("Early Head Start") program is to provide students a comprehensive, bilingual and multicultural community-based education that nurtures theirs intellectual, spiritual, physical, emotional, mental and social development.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.104</num>
      <heading>Office</heading>
      <text>The principle office of the Policy Council shall be on the Lac Courte Oreilles Indian Reservation.  The official address of the Policy Council is 8837N Trepania Road, Hayward, WI 54843. The Chairperson shall be the registered agent of the Policy Council.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.105</num>
      <heading>Effective Date</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this ordinance shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.106</num>
      <heading>Interpretation</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this ordinance:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be interpreted and applied as minimum requirements applicable to the educational related activities of the Tribe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.107</num>
      <heading>Severability And Non-Liability</heading>
      <text>If any section, provision or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this ordinance.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.108</num>
      <heading>Repeal Of Inconsistent Tribal Ordinances</heading>
      <text>All ordinances and resolutions inconsistent with this ordinance are hereby repealed. To the extent that this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, code, ordinance or regulation, the provisions of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>4.2</num>
    <heading>General Definitions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.201</num>
      <heading>General Definitions</heading>
      <text>The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><strong>"Meetings"</strong> means the meetings of the Policy Council including regular, special, and emergency meetings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><strong>"Policy Council"</strong> means the Policy Council of the Lac Courte Oreilles Head Start/Early Head Start Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text><strong>"Tribal Governing Board"</strong> means the Tribal Governing Board of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text><strong>"Tribe"</strong> means the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>4.3</num>
    <heading>General</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.301</num>
      <heading>Head Start And Early Head Start</heading>
      <text>The Head Start and Early Head Start is an important part of the ever-growing educational system of the Lac Courte Oreilles Ojibwe and supports the statement of philosophy of the Ojibwe Code for Long Life and Wisdom. Within the Head Start/Early Head Start program, the Tribe hereby commits itself to an early extended involvement in our children's educational and social development. The Tribal Governing Board hereby establishes and empowers the Lac Courte Oreilles Head Start and Early Head Start to carry out the intent of this ordinance as further defined herein:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Policy Council shall oversee the implementation of the Head Start Program Performance Standards established at 45 CFR § 1304.50, for which this Head Start/Early Head Start (HS/EHS) Policy Council is created. The Policy Council must perform the following functions directly:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Serve as a link to the Parent Committee, grantee agency governing bodies, public and private organizations, and the communities they serve to foster greater community participation and use of common resources.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Assist Parent Committee in communicating with parents enrolled in all program options to ensure that they understand their rights and responsibilities and the opportunities available in Head Start, and to encourage their participation in the program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Assist Parent Committee in planning, coordinating, and organizing program activities for parents with the assistance of staff, and ensure that funds set aside from program budgets are used to support parent activities (Parent Advisory Funds).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Assist in the recruiting of volunteer services from parents, community residents, and community organizations, and assist in the mobilization of community resources to meet identified needs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Establish and maintain procedures for working with the grantee or delegate agency to resolve community complaints about the program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Revise as necessary the budget while program is in operation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The general functions of the Lac Courte Oreilles Head Start/Early Head Start Policy Council in the oversight of the implementation of the Head Start Program Performance Standards established at 45 CFR § 1304.50, are to work in partnership with key management staff and the Tribal Governing Board to develop, review, and approve or disapprove the following policies and procedures:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All funding applications and amendments to funding applications for Head Start/Early Head Start, including administrative services, prior to the submission of such applications.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Procedures describing how the governing body and the appropriate policy group will implement shared decision making.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Procedures for program planning, program's philosophy, the long-range and short-range goals and objectives, to develop ways to meet them within the HHS guidelines.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The composition of the Policy Council and the procedures by which policy group members are chosen within HHS guidelines.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Criteria for defining recruitment, selection, and enrollment priorities, in accordance with the requirement of 45 CFR § 1305.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The annual self-assessment of the grantee agency's progress in carrying out the programmatic and fiscal intent of its grant application, including planning or other actions that may result from the review of the audit and findings from the federal monitoring.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Review the agency's procedures to ensure that an annual independent audit is conducted, in accordance with 45 CFR § 1301.31, and copies of the audit are available to them.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Program personnel policies and subsequent changes to those policies, including standards of conduct for program staff, consultants, and volunteers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Decisions to hire or terminate the Head Start/Early Head Start Director and any person who works primarily for the Head Start/Early Head Start Program. To make recommendations to the Tribal Governing Board to approve or disapprove final selections.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>To recommend revision of the Policy Council By-Laws when deemed necessary.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.302</num>
      <heading>Tribal Governing Board Liaison</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Governing Board, by formal action, shall appoint a Liaison(s) which shall be appointed to facilitate communication and coordination between the Tribal Governing Board and the Head Start/Early Head Start Program and the Policy Council. The Tribal Governing Board Liaison(s) shall not be considered a member of the Policy Council.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.303</num>
      <heading>Relationship To Tribe And Duration</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><u>Relationship</u>. The Policy Council is hereby delegated the authority to operate as a subordinate organization of the Tribal Governing Board pursuant to Article V, Section 1(m) of the Tribal Constitution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><u>Duration</u>. The duration of the Policy Council shall be perpetual, subject to dissolution by majority vote of the TGB.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.304</num>
      <heading>Policy Council</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><u>Organization</u>. The Policy Council shall be organized in accordance with the following guidelines:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 51% of the membership of the Policy Council shall be comprised of parents of currently enrolled children. Parents of all program options must be proportionally represented.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><u>Categories</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>This Policy Council shall be comprised of eight (8) parents of children presently enrolled in Head Start/Early Head Start Programs; four (4) from the Head Start Program, three (3) from the Early Head Start Program, one (1) from the Home Based Program; and two (2) Community Representatives. Parents from each Program Option shall cast a vote to elect their representative and all parents and community members may vote for the Community Representatives.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Community Representative nominees shall be from the local community; business; civic and professional organizations; and others who are familiar with resources and services for low-income children and families. Former Early Childhood Learning Center parents may also be community representatives.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pursuant to 45 CFR § l304.50(b)(6), no grantee or delegate agency staff (or members of their immediate family) may serve on Policy Council or Policy Committees except parents who occasionally substitute for regular Early Head Start /Head Start staff. In the case of Tribal Grantees, this exclusion applies only to Tribal staff that work in areas directly related to or which directly impact upon any Early Childhood Learning Center administrative, fiscal or programmatic issues.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text><u>Policy Council Member Eligibility</u>. Voting members of the Policy Council must meet the following criteria:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be at least eighteen (18) years of age at the time of his/her selection,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No grantee or delegate agency staff or members of their immediate family may serve on the Policy Council if he or she works in areas which directly impact or are directly related any Early Childhood Learning Center administrative, fiscal or programmatic issue,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Community Representatives shall be from the local community, business, civic or professional organizations, former Early Head Start parents, or others who are familiar with the resources and services for low-income children and families,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Not be convicted of a felony in federal or state court,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Not serve on another Early Head Start Policy Council,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Must possess a High School diploma or equivalency, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Represent at least one of the following categories: a parent, grandparent, great-grandparent or legal guardian of an enrolled student of the Early Head Start or the Lac Courte Oreilles community.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text><u>Quorum</u>. A majority of the voting Policy Council members then in office shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business at a meeting of the Policy Council. At any meeting of the Policy Council, each member, including the Chairperson of the Policy Council, shall have one (1) vote, and the vote of a majority of Policy Council members present at a duly held meeting at which a quorum is present shall constitute the action of the Policy Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text><u>Terms of Office</u>. Policy Council members shall serve for a term of one (1) year. No member shall serve on the Policy Council for more than three (3) one-year terms.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text><u>Voting Rights</u>. Each member of the Policy Council shall have on (1) vote. There shall be no proxy voting, by, or for, any member. Parents will constitute at least 51% voting membership of the PC.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text><u>Resignation</u>. A Policy Council member may resign by giving written notice to the registered agent of the Policy Council, who shall then promptly inform the members. In the event that the Chairperson wishes to resign, he or she shall give written notice to at least two (2) other members, who shall then promptly inform the other members. The resignation shall be effective upon its receipt by the Policy Council or at such alternate date as set forth in the notice of resignation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text><u>Removal</u>. With the approval of the Tribal Governing Board, the Policy Council may remove any Policy Council member for, but not limited to, the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Non-attendance of three (3) consecutive meetings without reasonable cause, as determined by the Policy Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conviction of a felony;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Breach of confidentiality.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text><u>Vacancy</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In the event of a vacancy, the parent who received the next highest number of votes in the most recent election shall fill the position within 30 days.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a vacancy is created by a community representative, the person receiving the next highest number of votes in the most recent election shall fill the position within 30 days.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding the foregoing, vacancies which occur within sixty (60) prior to the end of their term, shall not be replaced.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text><u>Miscellaneous</u>. No grantee agency staff (or members of their immediate families) may serve on the Policy Council except parents who occasionally substitute for regular Head Start/Early Head Start Staff. LCO Head Start/Early Head Start will abide by the Tribal Governing Board's definition of immediate family.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.305</num>
      <heading>Policy Council Operation And Compensation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Policy Council shall operate pursuant to the provisions of this ordinance, which provide for the internal regulation and management of the affairs of the Policy Council in a manner not inconsistent with tribal or federal law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Policy Council shall meet as often as necessary to conduct business but not less frequently than monthly.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Policy Council shall elect from within its membership at the first regularly called meeting following an election a Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson, and Secretary/Treasurer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>No officer of the Policy Council, any Policy Council member, or any other person shall have authority to bind the Policy Council except as authorized by the Policy Council through resolution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Policy Council members shall not receive a stipend for attending meetings.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.306</num>
      <heading>Elections</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><u>Process</u>. Nominations for the Policy Council shall be received by3:00 at the end of the third week of the new school year. Letters will be sent home with each child asking for nominations as well as advertisements in local media. Nominations will be received for the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Four (4) Head Start parents,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Three (3) Early Head Start parents,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>One (l) Home Based parent,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Two (2) Community representative from the local community: businesses; public or private community, civic, and professional organizations; and others who are familiar with resources and services for low-income children and families, including for example the parents of formerly enrolled children.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Elections will be held by the fifth Friday after the beginning of the new school year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Parents from each Early Head Start Program shall vote to elect their representative and all parents and community members shall vote to elect the community representatives. Elections of the Policy Council shall be held by the first Friday of September. In the event of a tie, a name will be selected by the Policy Council at the first scheduled meeting of the Policy Council.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.307</num>
      <heading>Care, Loyalty, And Conflict</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Policy Council members shall perform the duties and responsibilities and all other obligations under this Charter in good faith and in a manner believed to be in the best interests of the Policy Council, with such care and as an ordinary prudent person would use under similar circumstances in a like position, and in a manner loyal to the Policy Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Policy Council members shall, at all times, subordinate their personal interests to those of the Policy Council and shall avoid conflicts of interest, including without limitation, that no Policy Council member shall exploit business opportunities related to the business of the Policy Council for their own personal gain or profit without first presenting the same to the Policy Council or shall obtain any personal gain or profit from any transaction with the Policy Council without fully disclosing such involvement and benefit to the Policy Council and obtaining a waiver of any such conflict.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any Policy Council member appointed under this ordinance may engage in or be an officer, director, employee of other businesses or ventures, and may pursue business opportunities, provided that no benefit, advantage or information relative to any such opportunity was obtained in connection with or as the result of serving on the Policy Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>No Policy Council member shall commit any act with respect to the Policy Council that is illegal, fraudulent, or willfully unfair to either the Policy Council or Tribal Enterprises.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>4.4</num>
    <heading>Policy Council Officers</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.401</num>
      <heading>Officers</heading>
      <text>The Policy Council shall elect from within its membership at the first regularly scheduled meeting following an election: Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson, and Secretary/Treasurer.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.402</num>
      <heading>Officer Terms Of Office</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each officer shall be elected by quorum of the Policy Council once the full Council has been seated, and shall serve a term of one (1) year. All members may run for any officer position.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The officers shall be elected annually in a democratic fashion. Members are nominated for each officer position. Votes are cast by either verbally stating "Aye" or by secret ballot. The majority of votes shall decide each officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The officers of the Policy Council will be elected in October and seated in October when the outgoing member's term expires. This ensures that the newly seated members are trained and knowledgeable in their roles and responsibilities as a Policy Council member.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In the event of an officer vacancy, the successor shall be appointed by the Policy Council for the duration of the unexpired term.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.403</num>
      <heading>Removal</heading>
      <text>Any officer of the Policy Council who fails to perform the duties as outlined in this ordinance may be removed as an officer by a two-thirds vote of the Policy Council.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.404</num>
      <heading>Chairperson</heading>
      <text>The Chairperson shall preside at all meetings and maintain order. The Chairperson also serves on committees and coordinates activities as needed; works closely with the Head Start Director and Family and Community Partnership Coordinator as necessary; acts as the official representative of the Council; is knowledgeable of this ordinance, Head Start policies and requirements; and performs other duties as assigned. The Chairperson determines if a special meeting is necessary. The Chairperson shall have equal voting rights with the rest of the Council except when it involves a member of their family.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.405</num>
      <heading>Vice-Chairperson</heading>
      <text>The Vice-Chairperson shall preside in the absence of the Chairperson or whenever the Chairperson temporarily vacates the chair. In case of resignation or termination of the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson shall assume the office until a permanent chair is elected. The Vice-Chair also serves as a delegate to represent this group, and works with the Chairperson in all matters that concern the program and the Policy Council.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.406</num>
      <heading>Secretary/Treasurer</heading>
      <text>The Secretary shall record the minutes of every Policy Council meeting; maintain a file/record of minutes; assist the Chairperson in following the agenda, record and read motions as they are made; keep accurate records, and perform other duties as assigned.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>4.5</num>
    <heading>Committees</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.501</num>
      <heading>Committees</heading>
      <text>The Policy Council shall appoint such committees as are necessary to properly conduct business.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.502</num>
      <heading>Executive Committee</heading>
      <text>The Executive Committee shall be composed of the Officers of the Policy Council. The</text>
      <text>Executive Committee shall have the power to conduct business for the Policy Council between regular meetings of the Policy Council. Decisions shall be reviewed by the full Policy Council at the next meeting.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.503</num>
      <heading>Hiring Procedure</heading>
      <text>The Head Start Policy Council will utilize the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board for personnel issues. The selected Policy Council members, will screen, interview, and recommend persons to be hired to fill vacancies in the Head Start staff. A designated Policy Council member will then make recommendations to the Tribal Governing Board. The Tribal Governing Board has final approval or disapproval.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.504</num>
      <heading>Internal Grievance Committee</heading>
      <text>This committee shall hear grievances from the community, and from parents who have followed the grievance procedures established by the Governing Body and the Policy Council. These procedures are noted on the Community Grievance form. This committee may also hear grievances of Head Start staff and present their findings to the Tribal Governing Board. This committee will consist of a Coordinator, teacher, teacher's aid, Policy Council member, and a Parent Committee Officer.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.505</num>
      <heading>Special Committees</heading>
      <text>Special Committees may be appointed by the Chairperson of selected by the Council as the need arises.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>4.6</num>
    <heading>Meetings</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.601</num>
      <heading>Regular Meetings</heading>
      <text>Regular meetings of this Policy Council shall be held at least monthly as called by the Chairperson.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.602</num>
      <heading>Special/Call Meetings</heading>
      <text>There will be special meetings of the Policy Council only when there is a need, and all special meetings shall be called by the Chairperson at least 48 hours in advance. A phone call will be accepted in case of an emergency meeting that same day. The Chairperson or Vice-Chairperson will decide if the meeting is a true emergency.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.603</num>
      <heading>Notice Of Meetings</heading>
      <text>Written notices shall be mailed, e-mailed, or each member called at least five (5) days prior to the date of each regular meeting. A copy of the agenda for the meeting will also be enclosed. Members of the Policy Council will be notified of special meetings by telephone.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.604</num>
      <heading>Quorum</heading>
      <text>A majority of 51% of the members of the Council must be present to constitute a quorum in order to transact business for regular or special meetings.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>4.7</num>
    <heading>Order Of Business</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.701</num>
      <heading>Order Of Business</heading>
      <text>The regular meetings of the Committee shall follow said order of business:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Call to Order</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Roll Call</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Agenda Update</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Approval of Minutes</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Coordinator Reports. Coordinators are excused upon completion of reports, unless asked to remain. Coordinator Reports may include but are not limited to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Education</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Health and Transportation</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Disabilities</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Family and Community Partnership</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Directors Report. The Director is excused upon completion of report, unless asked to remain.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Special Items of Business</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Old Business</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>New Business</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Announcements</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Executive Session</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Adjournment</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>4.8</num>
    <heading>Amendments</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.801</num>
      <heading>Amendments</heading>
      <text>This ordinance may be amended by the Tribal Governing Board. Prior to amendment the Tribal Governing Board shall provide a copy of the proposed amendment to the Policy Council for its recommendation at least one (1) week before the meeting. The Policy Council may debate an amendment before a recommendation on adoption if provided to the Tribal Governing Board. All recommendations for approval of amendments must be recorded in the Policy Council Minutes.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
