<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <num>VEH</num>
  <heading>Vehicles</heading>
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <container>
    <num>VEH.3</num>
    <heading>Vehicle Licensing and Registration Code of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</heading>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.1</num>
      <heading>Motor Vehicle Registration Ordinance</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.1.010</num>
        <heading>Title</heading>
        <text>This ordinance shall be referred to as the LCO Motor Vehicle Registration Ordinance.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.1.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.1</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.1.020</num>
        <heading>Authority</heading>
        <text>LCO possesses the inherent sovereign authority to regulate its territory, and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(s)">Article V, Section 1(s) of the LCO constitution</cite> empowers the tribal governing board to "promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin and providing for the maintenance of law and order and the administration of justice by establishing a tribal court and defining its duties and powers."</text>
        <text>The Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians has the power and authority to license and register motor vehicles pursuant to its sovereign jurisdiction status and a reciprocal registration exemption agreement that has been entered into between the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and the State of Wisconsin with parallel laws and statutes for cross administration and enforcement purposes.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.1.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.2</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.1.030</num>
        <heading>Purpose and Policy</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this law is to create a system for enrolled Lac Courte Oreilles members to register their motor vehicles exclusively with the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation, for the issuance of Lac Courte Oreilles license plates to qualified applicants, and for the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to regulate the public roads within its sovereign jurisdiction. It is the policy of this law to clarify jurisdictional sovereignty and to generate revenue for the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.1.030 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.3</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.1.040</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction</heading>
        <text>Consistent with <cite path="IX|103">Chapter 103</cite> of the LCO Tribal Court Code of 2004, the LCO tribal court shall have jurisdiction over cases arising under this ordinance limited solely by the constitution and federal law.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.1.040 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.4</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.1.050</num>
        <heading>Construction</heading>
        <text>This ordinance shall be liberally construed to give full effect to the objectives and purposes for which it was enacted.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.1.050 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.5</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.1.060</num>
        <heading>Severability</heading>
        <text>If any provision of this ordinance, or the application thereof to any person, legal entity or circumstance, is held invalid or unenforceable, it shall be ineffective only to the extent of the invalidity, without affecting or impairing the validity and enforceability of the remainder of the provision or the remaining provisions of this ordinance.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.1.060 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.6</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.1.070</num>
        <heading>Repealer</heading>
        <text>This ordinance supersedes all prior animal control laws, codes, ordinances or regulations of LCO.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.1.070 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.7</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.1.080</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <text>Any term not defined in <cite path="§VEH.3.1.080">this section</cite> shall be given its ordinary meaning, and the below terms shall have the following meanings, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><strong>"Automobile" </strong>means any of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A motor vehicle designed and used primarily for carrying persons but which does not come within the definition of a motor bus, motorcycle, or moped.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A motor vehicle capable of speeds in excess of 30 miles per hour on a dry, level, hard surface with no wind, designed and built to have at least three (3) wheels in contact with the ground, a power source as an integral part of the vehicle, a curb weight of at least 1,600 pounds, and a passenger and operator area with sides permanently enclosed with rigid construction and a top which may be convertible.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><strong>"Department" </strong>means the Licensing Department, or any other department of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe, with the authority to implement, administer and enforce this law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><strong>"Gross weight" </strong>means the weight of the vehicle equipped for service plus the weight which the vehicle is carrying as load.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><strong>"Highway" </strong>means all public ways and thoroughfares and bridges on the same. It includes the entire width between the boundary lines of every way open to the use of the public as a matter of right for the purposes of vehicular travel.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text><strong>"Identification number" </strong>means the numbers, letters or combination of numbers and letters assigned by the manufacturer of a vehicle or vehicle part or by the department and stamped upon or affixed to a vehicle or vehicle part for the purpose of identification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text><strong>"Junked" </strong>means dismantled for parts or scrapped.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text><strong>"Lac Courte Oreilles" </strong>means Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text><strong>"Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal member" </strong>means a member of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians who is on the Lac Courte Oreilles enrollment list and has a Lac Courte Oreilles enrollment number.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text><strong>"Moped" </strong>means any of the following motor vehicles capable of speeds of not more than 30 miles per hour with a 150-pound rider on a dry, level hard surface with no wind, excluding a tractor, a power source as an integral part of the vehicle and a seat for the operator:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A bicycle-type vehicle with fully operative pedals for propulsion by human power and an engine certified by the manufacturer at not more than 50 cubic centimeters or an equivalent power unit.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A Type 1 motorcycle with an automatic transmission and an engine certified by the manufacturer at not more than 50 cubic centimeters or an equivalent power unit.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text><strong>"Motorcycle" </strong>means a motor vehicle, excluding a tractor or an all-terrain vehicle, which is capable of speeds in excess of 30 miles per hour with a 150-pound rider on a dry, level, hard surface with no wind, with a power source as an integral part of the vehicle, and which meets the conditions under par. (a) or (b):</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Type 1 is a motor vehicle which meets either of the following conditions:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Is designed and built with two (2) wheels in tandem and a seat for the operator, and may be modified to have no more than three (3) wheels by attaching a sidecar to one of the side the wheels in tandem without changing the location of the power source.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Is designed and built to have no more than three (3) wheels, seating for the operator and no more than three (3) passengers, and does not have the operator area enclosed.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Type 2 is a motor vehicle designed and built to have at least three (3) wheels in contact with the ground, a curb weight of less than 1,500 pounds, and a passenger and operator area with sides permanently enclosed with rigid construction and a top which may be convertible.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text><strong>"Motor home" </strong>means motor vehicle designed to be operated upon a highway for use as a temporary or recreational dwelling and having the same internal characteristics and equipment as a mobile home.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text><strong>"Nonresident" </strong>means a person not a resident of the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text><strong>"Other jurisdiction" or "another jurisdiction" </strong>means territory other than the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation, including the State of Wisconsin and any State other than Wisconsin.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text><strong>"Owner" </strong>means a person who holds the legal title of a vehicle, except that if legal title is held by a secured party with the immediate right of possession of the vehicle vested in the debtor, the debtor is the owner for the purposes of this law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text><strong>"Personal identifier" </strong>means a name, street address, post office box number or 9digit extended zip code.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text><strong>"Person with a disability that limits or impairs the ability to walk" </strong>means any person with a disability as defined by the federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, 42 USC 12101 et. seq., so far as applicable, or any persons who meet the following conditions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Cannot walk 200 feet or more without stopping to rest.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Cannot walk without the use of, or assistance from, another person or</text>
            <text>brace, cane, crutch, prosthetic device, wheelchair or other assistive device.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Is restricted by lung disease.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Uses portable oxygen.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Has cardiac condition to the extent that functional limitations are present.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Is severely limited in the ability to walk due to an arthritic neurological or</text>
            <text>orthopedic condition.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Has a degree of disability equal to that specified in pars. (1) to (6).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text><strong>"Reservation" </strong>means the Reservation of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin and includes all lands within the exterior boundaries and any other lands owned by the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text><strong>"Special interest vehicle" </strong>means a motor vehicle of any age which has not been altered or modified from original manufacturing specifications and, because of its historic interest, is being preserved by hobbyists.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text><strong>"Truck" </strong>means every motor vehicle 10,000 pounds or under designed, used or maintained primarily for the transportation of property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text><strong>"Vehicle" </strong>means every device in, upon or which any person or property is or may be transported or drawn upon a highway, except railroad trains. A snowmobile shall not be considered a vehicle except for purposes made specifically applicable by this law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.1.080 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.8</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.2</num>
      <heading>Registration Periods</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.2.010</num>
        <heading>Regular Automobiles</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All automobiles customarily owned by Lac Courte Oreilles tribal members shall be registered with the department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The annual fee for each automobile registered in this jurisdiction and under <cite path="§VEH.3.2.010">this section</cite> shall be $75.00 for two plates.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.2.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.9</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.2.020</num>
        <heading>Registration Periods for Private Automobiles</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All automobiles shall be registered by the department according to a monthly series system of registrations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>There are established 12 registration periods, each to be designated by a calendar month and to start on the first day of such month and end on the last day of the twelfth month from the date of commencing. The department shall so administer the monthly series system of registration so as to distribute the work of registering automobiles as uniformly as practicable throughout the calendar year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All automobiles subject to registration under monthly series systems shall be registered by the department for a period of twelve consecutive calendar months except as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>If the applicant holds current registration plates which were removed from an automobile which the applicant no longer owns or which has been junked, is no longer used on the highways or has been registered as a special interest vehicle or a reconstructed, replica, street modified or homemade vehicle and the plates were issued under the monthly series system, the department shall register the automobile which is the subject of the application for the remainder of the unexpired registration period.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>If the applicant does not hold current registration plates under the circumstances described in par. (a) and the application is an original rather than renewal application, the department may register the automobile which is subject to the application for such period or part thereof as the department determines will help to equalize the registration and renewal work load of the department.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All registration fees, applicable fines, penalties, forfeitures and assessments shall be paid to and retained by the department, for the operation of such department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The department shall be responsible for the administration of this ordinance and delegated authority to draft policies to allow for the full implementation of this law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All applications and registrations shall be retained by the department for one year after the application has been submitted or registration filed, thereafter all applications and registrations shall be retained by Lac Courte Oreilles for seven years.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.2.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.10</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.2.030</num>
        <heading>Special Registration Period for Vehicles Other than Private Automobiles</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The department shall require that any vehicle other than private automobiles, be registered according to the monthly series system of registration prescribed by <cite path="§VEH.3.2.030">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>There are established 12 registration periods, each to be designed by a calendar month and to start on the first day of such month and end on the last day of the 12th month from the date of commencing. The department shall so administer the monthly series system of registration as to distribute the work of registration throughout the calendar year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All vehicles subject to registration under the monthly series system under <cite path="§VEH.3.2.030">this section</cite> shall be registered by the department for a period of 12 consecutive calendar months except as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>If the applicant holds registration plates which were removed from a vehicle under section 22 and the plates were issued under the monthly series system, the department shall register a replacement vehicle of the same type and gross weight which is the subject of the application for the remainder of the unexpired registration period.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>If the applicant does not hold current registration plates under the circumstances described in par. (1) and the application is an original rather than renewal application, the department may register the vehicle which is the subject of the application for such period or part of a period as the department determines will help to equalize the registration and renewal workload of the department.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><cite path="§VEH.3.11.010">Section VEH.3.11.010</cite> applies to any vehicles registered according to the monthly series system under <cite path="§VEH.3.2.030">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.2.030 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.11</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.2.040</num>
        <heading>Biennial Registration</heading>
        <text>The following vehicles shall be registered on a biennial basis:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A motorcycle or moped, as specified in <cite path="§VEH.3.7.040">Section VEH.3.7.040</cite>. The registration period for a motorcycle or moped begins on May 1 of an even-numbered year and ends on April 30 of the next even numbered year.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.2.040 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.12</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.2.050</num>
        <heading>Vehicles Exempt from Registration</heading>
        <text>A vehicle even though operated on a highway of the Reservation, is exempt from registration when such vehicle is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Operated in accordance with the provisions exempting nonresident or foreign registered vehicles from registration, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A farm tractor used exclusively in agricultural operations, including threshing, or used exclusively to provide power to drive other machinery, or to transport from job to job machinery driven by such tractor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A trailer or semi-trailer used exclusively for the transportation of farm machinery, implements, produce or supplies on a farm or between farms; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A fork-lift truck, a specially constructed road or truck tractor used for shunting trailers or semi-trailer used exclusively for the transportation of farm machinery, implements, produce or supplies on a farm or between farms; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A trailer or camping trailer having a gross weight of 3,000 pounds or less and not used for hire or rental; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A trailer not operated in conjunction with a motor vehicle; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A new motor vehicle being operated only across a highway from point of manufacture or assembly; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>A piece of road machinery.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.2.050 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.13</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.3</num>
      <heading>Application for Registration</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.3.010</num>
        <heading>Applications in General</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Application for original registration and for renewal of registration shall be made to the department upon forms prescribed by it and shall be accompanied by the required fee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The forms for application for original registration and for renewal of registration shall be provided by the department and shall include a place for an applicant or registrant under <cite path="VEH|VEH.3">this chapter</cite> to designate that the applicant's or registrant's name, street address, post-office box number and 9-digit extended zip code may not be disclosed, a statement indicating the effect of making such a designation and a place for an applicant or registrant who made a designation under this subsection to reverse the designation.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.3.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.14</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.3.020</num>
        <heading>Original Applications</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applications for original registration of a vehicle shall contain the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The name of the owner.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A description of the vehicle, including make, model, identification number and any other information which the department may reasonably require for proper identification of the vehicle.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Such further information as the department may reasonably require to enable it to determine whether the vehicle is by law entitled to registration or to enable it to determine the proper registration fee for the vehicle.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The department may accept an application and complete registration of a vehicle when the evidence of ownership is held by a nonresident lien holder or for other reasons not immediately available if the department is satisfied as to ownership of the vehicle. The title fee shall be collected at the time of registration and retained even though certificate of title is not issued.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.3.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.15</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.3.030</num>
        <heading>Applicants Under 18</heading>
        <text>If the applicant for a certificate of registration is under 18 years of age, the application shall be accompanied by a statement made and signed by either of the applicant's parents, if such parent has custody of the minor; or if neither parent has custody, then by the person having custody, stating that the applicant has the signer's consent to register the vehicle in the applicant's name. The signature on the statement shall not impute any liability for the negligence of misconduct of the applicant while operating such motor vehicle on the highways. Any person who violates <cite path="§VEH.3.3.030">this section</cite> may be required to forfeit not more than $200.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.3.030 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.16</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.3.040</num>
        <heading>Renewal Applications</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applications for renewal of registration shall contain the information required in <cite path="§VEH.3.3.010|(a)">Section VEH.3.3.010(a)</cite> for original applications, or such parts thereof as the department deems necessary to assure the proper registration of the vehicle. The department may require that applications for renewal of registration be accompanied by the certificate of title issued for the vehicle only when the true ownership or proper registration of the vehicle is in doubt and cannot be resolved from records maintained by the department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 30 days prior to the expiration of a vehicle's registration, the department shall mail to the last-known address of the registrant a notice of the date upon which the registration must be renewed and an application form for renewal of registration.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The application form or an accompanying document shall include a list of any unpaid citations for nonmoving traffic violations, or any violations of administrative rules of the department, or parking violations, entered against the registrant which remains unpaid.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>If there is a citation for any nonmoving traffic violation entered against the registrant which is unpaid, he or she shall be notified that the vehicle may not be registered until the citation is paid or the registrant appears in court to respond to the citation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.3.040 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.17</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.3.050</num>
        <heading>Grounds for Refusing Registration</heading>
        <text>The department shall refuse registration of a vehicle under any of the following circumstances:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The vehicle owner applying for registration is not a Lac Courte Oreilles member, does not reside on the Reservation and/or the vehicle is not customarily kept on the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The required vehicle registration fee imposed by the department for a vehicle customarily kept on the Reservation and owned by an enrolled Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal member, has not been paid for the specific vehicle, and the department may refuse registration of a vehicle if such fees for the current period or for any previous period for which payment of a registration fee is required by law have not been paid on any other vehicles owned or leased by the applicant for registration.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The applicant has failed to furnish any of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Unless exempted by rule of the document, the mileage disclosure from the most recent titled owner and of all subsequent non-titled owners of the vehicle.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Other information or documents required by law or by the department pursuant to authority of law.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Proof of Lac Courte Oreilles membership by enrollment card or number.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Where the applicant does not hold a valid certificate of title and is not entitled to the issuance of a certificate of title.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The applicant's registration has been suspended or revoked and such suspension or revocation still is in effect.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The vehicle is exempt from registration and voluntary registration of the vehicle is not expressly authorized.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.3.050 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.18</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.4</num>
      <heading>Registration Plates</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.4.010</num>
        <heading>Design, Procurement and Issuance of Registration Plates</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The department upon registering a vehicle pursuant to <cite path="§VEH.3.2.010">Section VEH.3.2.010</cite> and <cite path="§VEH.3.11.010">Section VEH.3.11.010</cite> shall issue to the applicant two (2) registration plates for an automobile, truck, motor home, and one plate for other vehicles. The department upon registering a vehicle pursuant to any other section shall issue one plate unless the department determines that two (2) plates will better serve the interests of law enforcement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All registration plates shall have displayed upon them the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The registration number assigned to the vehicle or owner. The registration number shall be composed of numbers or letters or both.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The name "Lac Courte Oreilles"</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>An indication of the period for which the specific plate is issued or the date of expiration of registration.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In lieu of issuing a new plate upon each renewal of registration of a vehicle, the department may issue one insert tag, decal or other identification per vehicle to indicate the period of registration. The tag, decal or other identification shall be provided by the department and used only if the outstanding plate is in suitable condition for further usage.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.4.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.19</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.4.020</num>
        <heading>Application for and Issuance of Special Plates</heading>
        <text>The department shall issue special plates as specified in <cite path="§VEH.3.4.020">this section</cite> under the following circumstances:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Disabled Lac Courte Oreilles Residents.</heading>
          <text>If any Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal member, who is a resident of the Reservation and who is registering or has registered an automobile or truck or a motor home, submits a statement once every four (4) years, from a physician licensed to practice medicine in any state, or from a chiropractor licensed to practice chiropractic in any state, that the resident is a person with a disability that limits or impairs the ability to walk, the department shall procure, issue and deliver to the disabled person plates of a special design in lieu of plates which ordinarily would be issued for the vehicle, and shall renew the plates. The plates shall be so designed as to readily apprize law enforcement officers of the fact that the vehicle is owned by a nonveteran disabled person and is entitled to parking privileges specified in other laws. No charge in addition to the registration fee shall be made for the issuance or renewal of such plates.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Disabled Lac Courte Oreilles Veterans.</heading>
          <text>If any resident of the Reservation who is registering or has registered an automobile, truck, or a motor home submits a statement once every four (4) years, from the Lac Courte Oreilles Department of Veterans Affairs certifying to the department that the resident is, by reason of injuries sustained while in the active U.S. military service, a person with a disability that limits or impairs the ability to walk, the department shall procure, issue and deliver to the veteran, plates of a special design in lieu of the plates which ordinarily would be issued for the vehicle, and shall renew the plates. The plates shall be so designed as to readily apprize law enforcement officers of the fact that the vehicle is owned by a disabled veteran and is entitled to parking privileges specified in other laws. No charge in addition to the registration fee shall be made for the issuance or renewal of such plates.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Lac Courte Oreilles Veteran/Congressional Medal of Honor.</heading>
          <text>Upon application by any person awarded the congressional medal of honor and submission of proper proof thereof, the department shall issue special plates so designed as to indicate such award. No charge shall be made for the issuance of such plates which have a non-expiring registration period.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Prisoner of War.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Upon application to register an automobile or truck by any Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal member residing on the Reservation who was a member of any of the U.S. armed services and who was held as a prisoner of war during any of the conflicts described as World War II, Vietnam, Persian Gulf, Operation Desert (Shield) Storm, or in Grenada, Lebanon, Panama, Somalia or a Middle East crisis, and upon submission of a statement from the Lac Courte Oreilles Department of Veterans Affairs certifying that the person was a prisoner of war during one of the conflicts described, the department shall issue to the person a special plate which is colored (to be determined by the department) and which has the words "ex-prisoner of war" placed on the plate in the manner designated by the department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A person who maintains no more than one registration under this subsection at one time shall not be charged a fee for registration of the vehicle or issuance of plates.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>For each additional vehicle, a person who maintains more than one registration under this subsection at one time shall be charged a fee of $15.00 for issuance of the plates in addition to the annual registration fee for the vehicle.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>If a registration plate has been issued to a person under par (1), upon application by the surviving spouse of the person, the department may permit the surviving spouse to retain the plate. If the plate has been returned to the department or surrendered to another state, the department may reissue the plate to the surviving spouse. The department shall charge an additional fee of $15.00 to reissue the plate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The department shall charge a fee of $15.00 for re-issuance of any plate under par. (4).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <heading>Veterans Plates.</heading>
          <text>The department shall issue special veterans/military plates under this subsection for the following authorized special groups.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>World War II veterans, Korean War veterans, Vietnam War veterans, Persian Gulf War veterans, Air force Retired, Air force Veteran, Army Retired, Army Veteran, U.S. Coast Guard, Marine Corps Retired, Marine Corps Veteran, Navy Retired, Navy Veteran, Purple Heart, Medal of Honor</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The annual registration fee shall be $40.00. There shall be an additional fee of $10.00 for the issuance of the initial registration of Special Veteran/Military plates. $40.00 plus $10.00 for the first plate. Renewal fees for these plates shall be $40.00.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>If an individual in possession of special plates or of personalized plates under <cite path="§VEH.3.4.020">this section</cite> does not maintain membership in the applicable authorized special groups during the year which is not a plate issuance year the individual shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Dispose of the special plates in a manner prescribed by the department;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>In addition to the regular application fee, pay a $4 fee for the issuance of replacement plates; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Return the certificate of title to the department for correction.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.4.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.20</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.4.030</num>
        <heading>Personalized License Plates</heading>
        <text>In <cite path="§VEH.3.4.030">this section</cite>, "personalized registration plates" means either of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A registration plate for a motor vehicle registered under this ordinance which displays a registration composed of letters or numbers, or both, requested by the applicant. Personalized registration plates under this paragraph shall be of the same color and design as regular registration plates and shall consist of numbers or letters, or both, not exceeding 5 positions and not less than one position for a plate issued for a motorcycle or not exceeding 7 positions and not less than 1 position for all other plates.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A registration plate of the same color and design as provided in <cite path="§VEH.3.4.020">Section VEH.3.4.020</cite> for a vehicle specified under <cite path="§VEH.3.4.020">Section VEH.3.4.020</cite> which displays the applicable symbol of the authorized special group to which the person belongs and a registration number composed of letters or numbers, or both, not exceeding 6 positions and not less than 1 position, requested by the applicant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The department shall issue personalized registration plates only upon request and if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The request and alternate thereto is received by the department in writing by mail by the 15th day of the month in which the vehicle is to be registered;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The request is accompanied by the proper fee, an application for original or renewal vehicle registration and the proper registration fee;</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The requested combination of numbers or letters has not already been issued.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>In addition to the regular application fee provided for in this ordinance, the applicant for a personalized registration plate issued on an annual basis shall pay a fee of $15 for the issuance of the plate and $15 in each succeeding year to maintain the plate.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Each personalized registration plate issued shall be reserved for the recipient in succeeding registration periods and shall not be duplicated for issuance to any other person if the recipient maintains the plate, unless the recipient authorizes the issuance of the plate to another person. If the recipient does not maintain the plate for two successive years which are not plate issuance years or if the recipient does not specifically request re-issuance of the personalized license plate by the end of the month in which the plate expires in a plate issuance year, the department may reissue the personalized registration plate to another applicant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If an individual in possession of a personalized registration plate does not maintain the personalized registration plate during a year which is not plate issuance year, the individual shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Dispose of the personalized plate in a manner prescribed by the department;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>In addition to the regular application fee, pay a $4 fee for the issuance of replacements plates; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Return the certificate of title to the department for correction.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The department may refuse to issue any combination of letters or numbers, or both, which carry connotations offensive to Lac Courte Oreilles heritage or traditions, to good taste or decency, or which would be misleading or in conflict with the issuance of any other registration plates. All decisions of the department with respect to personalized registration plate applications shall be final and not subject to judicial review.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The department may cancel and order the return of any personalized registration plates issued which contain any combination of letters or numbers, or both, which the department determines may carry connotations that are offensive to the Lac Courte Oreilles heritage or traditions, good taste and decency or which may be misleading. Any person ordered to return such plate shall either be reimbursed for any additional fees they paid for the plates for the registration year in which they are recalled, or be given at no additional cost replacement personalized registration plates, the issuance of which is in compliance with this ordinance. A person who fails to return personalized registration plates upon request of the department may be required forfeit not more than $200.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.4.030 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.21</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.5</num>
      <heading>Display of Registration Plates</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.5.010</num>
        <heading>Placement of Plates or Decals on Vehicles</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whenever two (2) registration plates are licensed for a vehicle, one (1) plate shall be attached to the front and one (1) to the rear of the vehicle. Whenever only one (1) registration plate is issued for a vehicle, the plate shall be attached to the rear.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any registration decal or tag issued by the department shall be placed on the rear registration plate of the vehicle in the manner directed by the department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Registration plates shall be attached firmly and rigidly in a horizontal position and conspicuous place. The plates shall at all times be maintained in a legible condition and shall be so displayed that they can be readily and distinctly read. Any peace officer may require the operator of any vehicle on which plates are not properly displayed to display such plates as required by <cite path="§VEH.3.5.010">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any of the following may be required to forfeit not more than $200:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A person who operates a vehicle for which a current registration plate or insert tag has been issued without such plate or tag being attached to the vehicle.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A person who operates a vehicle with a registration plate attached in a nonrigid or non-horizontal manner or in an inconspicuous place so as to make it difficult to see and read the plate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>A person who operates a vehicle with the registration plate in an illegible condition due to the accumulation of dirt or other foreign matter.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.5.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.22</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.6</num>
      <heading>Issuance of Replacement Plates</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.6.010</num>
        <heading>Lost or Destroyed Plates</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whenever a current registration plate is lost or destroyed, the owner of the vehicle to which the plate was attached shall immediately apply to the department for replacement. Except as further provided in <cite path="§VEH.3.6.010">this section</cite>, upon satisfactory proof of the loss or destruction of each plate and upon payment of a fee of $4.00 for each plate, the department shall issue a replacement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon satisfactory proof of the loss or destruction of a specialized plate or a personalized plate issued under <cite path="§VEH.3.4.030">Section VEH.3.4.030</cite>, and upon payment of a fee of $4.00 for each plate, the department shall issue a replacement.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.6.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.23</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.6.020</num>
        <heading>Illegible Plates</heading>
        <text>Whenever a current registration plate becomes illegible, the owner of the vehicle to which the plate is attached shall apply to the department for a replacement. Upon receipt of satisfactory proof of illegibility, and upon payment of a fee of $2 for each plate, the department shall issue a replacement. Upon receipt of a replacement plate, the applicant shall return the illegible plate to the department for recycling.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.6.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.24</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.6.030</num>
        <heading>Replacement Plates</heading>
        <text>When issuing a replacement plate, the department may assign a new number and issue a new plate rather than a duplicate of the original if in its judgment that is in the best interests of economy or prevention of fraud. Upon receipt of a replacement plate, the applicant shall return the illegible plate to the department for recycling. Any person issued replacement plates who fail to return the original plates to the department as required by <cite path="§VEH.3.6.030">this section</cite> may be required to forfeit not more than $200.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.6.030 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.25</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.7</num>
      <heading>Department to Compile Registration Lists</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.7.010</num>
        <heading>Maintaining Lists</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At intervals selected by the department, the department shall compile a list of registrations made during that interval pursuant to the monthly series system of registering automobiles. The list shall give the name and address of each registrant, the registration number assigned, and other identifying information as the department deems necessary.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The department shall compile a list of new automobile and motor truck registrations. Registrations for other new vehicles may be included if deemed necessary by the department. Such lists shall be compiled at such intervals during the month as is deemed necessary by the department but the final list compiled each month shall include the listing of the last day of the month. Such list shall contain only those vehicles being registered for the first time after sale by a dealer. Such list shall contain the name and address of the owner, the make, body type, identification number of the vehicle, and the date of sale.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.7.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.26</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.7.020</num>
        <heading>Access to Lists</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon request, the department shall distribute free of charge registration lists compiled under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.020">this section</cite> as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>To the Lac Courte Oreilles Law Enforcement Department, one copy of each automobile registration list under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.010">Section VEH.3.7.010</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>To any other public officer or agency that provides in writing reasonable requests for the lists, one copy of each automobile registration list under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.010">Section VEH.3.7.010</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in <cite path="§VEH.3.7.030">Section VEH.3.7.030</cite> public officers and agencies receiving free copies of registration lists under par. (a) shall keep such lists current and open to public inspection.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.7.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.27</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.7.030</num>
        <heading>Limitations on Disclosure</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In providing copies under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.030">this section</cite> of any written information collected or prepared under this law which consists in whole or in part of the personal identifiers of 10 or more persons, the department may not disclose a personal identifier of any person who has made a designation that his or her personal identifiers may not be disclosed as provided in <cite path="§VEH.3.7.030">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Paragraph (a) does not apply to any of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A person receiving a registration list under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.020|(a)">Section VEH.3.7.020(a)</cite> and <cite path="§VEH.3.7.020|(b)">Section VEH.3.7.020(b)</cite> to perform a legally authorized function.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A law enforcement agency</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>An insurer authorized to write property and casualty insurance in the State of Wisconsin or an agent of the insurer, if the insurer or agent uses the personal identifier designated for non-disclosure under <cite path="§VEH.3.2.050|(b)">Section VEH.3.2.050(b)</cite> for purposes of issuing or renewing a policy and related underwriting, billing or processing or paying a claim.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>A person obtaining registration or title information for use in the conduct of a vehicle recall by the manufacturer of the vehicle or an agent of the manufacturer, if the person uses the personal identifiers designated for nondisclosure under <cite path="§VEH.3.2.050|(b)">Section VEH.3.2.050(b)</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any person who has received under par. (b) a personal identifier of any person who has made a designation under <cite path="§VEH.3.2.050|(b)">Section VEH.3.2.050(b)</cite> shall keep the personal identifier confidential and may not disclose it except for a purpose applicable to that person under par. (b).</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any person who willfully discloses a personal identifier in violation of <cite path="§VEH.3.7.030">this section</cite> may be subject to a fine of not more than $500 for each violation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any person who willfully requests or obtains a personal identifier from the department under this subsection under false pretenses may be required to forfeit not more than $500 for each violation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.7.030 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.28</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.7.040</num>
        <heading>Biennial Motorcycle Fees</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For each motorcycle or moped with a curb weight of 1,499 pounds or less, which is designed for the transportation of persons rather than property, a biennial fee of $23.00.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Registration plates under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.040">this section</cite> expire on April 30 of even numbered years.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>One license plate is sent by the department of each cycle registered.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.7.040 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.29</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.7.050</num>
        <heading>Calculation of Registration Fees Relating to Gross Weight: Trucks</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Unless otherwise noted, for each truck under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.050">this section</cite>, a yearly registration fee is to be determined on the basis of the maximum gross weight of the vehicle. Each vehicle registered will receive one license plate. Maximum gross weight shall be determined by adding together the weight in pounds of the vehicle when equipped to carry a load as a motor truck and the maximum load in pounds which the applicant proposes to carry on the vehicle when used as a motor truck.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The following schedule shall be used in determining fees based on gross weight, provided that a surcharge of $18 shall be added to and collected with the fee for each truck.</text>
          <text>
            <table>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>Maximum gross weight in pounds</td>
                  <td>Annual Fee</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 4,500</td>
                  <td>$ 75</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 6,000</td>
                  <td>$ 84</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 8,000</td>
                  <td>$ 106</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 10,000</td>
                  <td>$ 155</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>In excess of 10,000</td>
                  <td>Vary by vehicle weight</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.7.050 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.30</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.7.060</num>
        <heading>Motor Homes</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Unless otherwise noted, for each mobile home under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.060">this section</cite>, a yearly registration fee is to be determined on the basis of the gross weight of the mobile home. Each mobile home registered will receive one license plate.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The following schedule shall be used in determining fees based on gross weight, provided that a surcharge of $20 shall be added to and collected with the fee for each mobile home.</text>
          <text>
            <table>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>Gross weight in pounds:</td>
                  <td>Annual Fee:</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 5,000</td>
                  <td>$ 48.50</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 8,000</td>
                  <td>$ 55</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 12,000</td>
                  <td>$ 67.50</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 16,000</td>
                  <td>$ 80.50</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 20,000</td>
                  <td>$ 93.50</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Not more than 26,000</td>
                  <td>$ 106.50</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>More than 26,000</td>
                  <td>$ 119.50</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Upon payment of the fee prescribed by law, a vehicle subject to registration on the basis of gross weight may be registered at a weight in excess of the manufacturer's maximum gross weight rating, but such registration does not exempt such vehicle from compliance with weight limitations imposed by law or by state, local or tribal authorities pursuant to authority of law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.7.060 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.31</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.8</num>
      <heading>Special Registration Fees for Certain Vehicles</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.8.010</num>
        <heading>Lac Courte Oreilles Government Vehicles</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A fee of $5 shall be paid to the department for the original issuance of a non-expiring registration plate for any vehicle owned by the Lac Courte Oreilles and operated exclusively in service of the public.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A fee of $5 shall be paid to the department for the original issuance of a non-expiring registration plate for vehicles used by the Lac Courte Oreilles Law Enforcement Department exclusively in the performance of their duties.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.8.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.32</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.9</num>
      <heading>Antique Motor Vehicles; Registration, Plates, Use</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.9.010</num>
        <heading>Antique Motor Vehicles</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any person who is a resident of the Reservation and the owner or subsequent transferee of a motor vehicle which has a model year of 1945 or earlier and which has not been altered or modified from the original manufacturer's specifications may upon, application register the same as an antique vehicle upon payment of a fee of $5, and be furnished non-expiring registration plates of a distinctive design, in lieu of the usual registration plates, which shall show in addition to the registration number that the vehicle is an antique. The registration shall be valid while the vehicle is owned by the applicant without payment of any additional fee. The vehicle shall only be used for special occasions such as display and parade purposes or for necessary testing, maintenance and storage purposes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any person who registers an antique motor vehicle under par. (a) may furnish and display on the vehicle a historical plate from or representing the model year of the vehicle if the registration and plates issued by the department are simultaneously carried in the vehicle and are available for inspection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Unless inconsistent with <cite path="§VEH.3.9.010">this section</cite>, the provisions applicable to other motor vehicles apply to antique motor vehicles.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.9.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.33</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.10</num>
      <heading>Special Interest Vehicles: Registration, Plates, Use</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.10.010</num>
        <heading>Special Interest Vehicle/Collectors Special Vehicle</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any person who is the owner of a special interest vehicle which is 20 or more years old at the time of making application for registration or transfer of title of the vehicle and who, has registered in Lac Courte Oreilles and uses for regular transportation at least one vehicle that has regular registration plates may upon application register the vehicle as a special interest vehicle upon payment of a fee under par. (b).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The fee to register a collector vehicle under par. (a) is a one time fee of $50.00 plus twice the regular annual fee for the vehicle type. The registration period is non expiring.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Collector special plates are available to LCO tribal members with a valid collector vehicle and are available for autos, motor homes, motor trucks up through 8,000 pounds and 12,000 pound farm trucks. The fee to register a collector special vehicle is subject to the annual registration fee dependent on the vehicle type plus $15 dollars when new plates are issued.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The department shall furnish the owner of the vehicle with registrations plates of a distinctive design in lieu of the usual registration plates, and those shall show that the vehicle is a special interest vehicle owned by a collector.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Each collector applying for special interest vehicle registration plates will be issued a collector's identification number which will appear on each plate. Second and all subsequent registrations under <cite path="§VEH.3.10.010">this section</cite> by the same collector will bear the same collector's identification number followed by a suffix letter for vehicle identification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The vehicle may be used as are other vehicles of the same type except:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Motor vehicles may not transport passengers for hire.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Trucks may not haul material weighing more than 500 pounds.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>No special interest vehicle may be operated upon any highway within the Reservation during the month of January unless the owner of the vehicle reregisters the vehicle with regular registration plates or transfers regular registration plates to the vehicle.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Unless inconsistent with <cite path="§VEH.3.10.010">this section</cite>, the provisions applicable to other vehicles shall apply to special interest vehicles.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.10.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.34</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.11</num>
      <heading>Part-Year Fees for Private Automobiles</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.010</num>
        <heading>Calculation of Partial Fees</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant for registration of an automobile under the monthly series system shall pay in full the annual registration fee prescribed by law, except as otherwise provided in <cite path="§VEH.3.11.010">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the applicant for registration holds current registration plates which were removed from an automobile which the applicant no longer owns or which has been junked, is no longer being used on the highways or has been registered as a special interest vehicle the applicant is exempt from the payment of a registration fee, except in the following cases:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>If the annual fee prescribed for the automobile being registered is higher than the annual fee prescribed for the automobile from which the plates were removed, the applicant shall pay a fee computed on the basis of one-twelfth of the difference between the two annual fees multiplied by the number of months for which the automobile which is the subject of the application is being registered. The start of the new registration, for the purpose of computing the fee, shall be determined in accordance with par. (c).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of computing the registration fee payable upon registration of an automobile under circumstances described in par. (a) &amp; (b), the beginning of the current registration period shall be determined as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>If the first operation of an automobile under circumstances making the owner liable for its registration by the Department occurs on or before the 15th day of a given month, the registration period commences on the first day of such month. If the first operation occurs on or after the 16th day of a given month, the registration period commences on the first day of the following month. "First operation" means operation of an automobile for the first time after it was transferred to the applicant or after it was registered in another jurisdiction or after the expiration of 12 months of non-operation since expiration of the last registration by the Department or after it was no longer used on the highways.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>In the case of an automobile which has not previously been registered or which has not been registered by the Department by the present owner since the last owner last acquired ownership of the automobile, the Department shall assume that the date of first operation within the meaning of sub. (1) is the date of the bill of sale evidencing the transfer of ownership to the applicant unless the applicant files with the department a statement that the automobile was not so operated until a later date, specifying the date of such first operation. In the case of at least 12 months of non-operation of an automobile previously registered by the applicant, the applicant must file with the department a statement that he or she did not operate or consent to the operation of the automobile under circumstances making it subject to registration in this state during such 12-month period and must specify the date following such period when the automobile was first so operated. The department may refuse to accept a statement which projects the date of first operation into the future.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.35</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.020</num>
        <heading>When Part-Period Fees Payable for Vehicles Other than Automobiles;</heading>
        <text>
          <strong>Computation of Part-Period Fees</strong>
        </text>
        <text>The annual registration fee shall be paid in full on all vehicles registered pursuant to <cite path="§VEH.3.2.030">Section VEH.3.2.030</cite>, unless the vehicles come within one of the following categories, in which event the applicant is liable for the payment of only a part-period fee to be computed in accordance with <cite path="§VEH.3.11.020|(e)">Section VEH.3.11.020(e)</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The vehicle has not previously been registered within this Reservation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The vehicle previously was registered within this Reservation; but</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The vehicle in the meantime has been registered in another jurisdiction and such foreign registration was in effect during or subsequent to the expiration of the previous registration in this state; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The vehicle was transferred to the applicant after the expiration of the last registration in this state; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>At least 12 months have elapsed since the end of the period for which the vehicle previously was registered and the applicant files with the department a statement that did not, during such 12-month period, operate or consent to the operation of the vehicle under circumstances making the vehicle subject to registration in this state; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The vehicle is a motorcycle which has been transferred to the applicant and for which current registration plates had been issued to the previous owner; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The vehicle which has been transferred to the applicant is a motor home or a truck; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The vehicle is subject to the provisions of sub. (5); or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The vehicle is a replacement for a registered vehicle which has been junked or is no longer used on the highway; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The vehicle is owned by a person who has been in active military service and less than 12 months of non-operation have elapsed since the end of the period for which the vehicle was previously registered, provided the applicant files with the department a statement of such non-operation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Part-period registration fees shall be computed as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>For vehicles registered under the conditions in <cite path="§VEH.3.11.020|(a)">Section VEH.3.11.020(a)</cite>, <cite path="§VEH.3.11.020|(b)">Section VEH.3.11.020(b)</cite>, or <cite path="§VEH.3.11.020|(d)">Section VEH.3.11.020(d)</cite>, the fee for the current registration period shall be computed on the basis of one-twelfth of the annual registration fee or one twenty-fourth of the biennial registration fee prescribed for the vehicle multiplied by the number of months of the current registration period which have not fully expired on the date the vehicle first is operated by or with the consent of the applicant under circumstances making it subject to registration by the Lac Courte Oreilles. In the case of a vehicle which has not previously been registered or which has not been registered within this Reservation by the present owner since the owner last acquired ownership of the vehicle, the department shall assume that the date of first operation bill of sales evidencing transfer of ownership to the applicant unless he or she files with the department a statement that the vehicle was not so operated until a later date, specifying the date of such first operation. The department may refuse to accept any statement which projects the date of first operation into the future.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>For the registration of a replacement vehicle under the conditions set forth in <cite path="§VEH.3.11.020|(c)">Section VEH.3.11.020(c)</cite>, or the fee shall be computed as for a vehicle not previously registered in this state, but a credit shall be allowed for the unused portion of the fee paid for the vehicle being replaced. Such credit shall be computed on the basis of one-twelfth of the annual registration fee or one twenty-fourth of the biennial registration fee prescribed for the vehicle being replaced multiplied by the number of months of registration which have not fully expired at the time the vehicle being replaced was junked, traded, sold or removed from jurisdiction of the Lac Courte Oreilles. Except for a vehicle registered on a biennial basis, it is not necessary that the replacement vehicle be of the same type as the one being replaced in order for the applicant to take advantage of the credit but the credit may be applied toward registration of the replacement vehicle only up to the date when the registration of the vehicle being replaced would have expired.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.36</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.030</num>
        <heading>Transferred Plates or Plates No Longer in Use</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The transferee of a vehicle registered as provided in <cite path="§VEH.3.2.030">Section VEH.3.2.030</cite> is not subject to the payment of any registration fee for the remainder of the period for which the vehicle is registered unless, by reason of his or her status or the use to which the vehicle is put, the fee prescribed by law is higher than that paid by the former owner. In such event, the fee shall be computed on the basis of one-twelfth of the difference between the two (2) annual fees multiplied by the number of months of the current registration period which have not fully expired on the date, after the vehicle is acquired by the applicant, when such vehicle is first operated by him or her with his or her consent under circumstances making it subject to registration by the Lac Courte Oreilles.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person retaining a set of plates removed from a vehicle which was junked or transferred, is no longer used on the highways or has been registered as a special interest vehicle under <cite path="§VEH.3.10.010">Section VEH.3.10.010</cite> may receive credit for the unused portion of the registration fee paid when registering a replacement vehicle of the same type and gross weight.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A person retaining a set of plates removed from a motorcycle may receive credit for the unused portion of the registration fee paid when registering a replacement motorcycle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><cite path="§VEH.3.11.030">This section</cite> does not apply to vehicles registered at a fee of $5 under <cite path="§VEH.3.8.010">Section VEH.3.8.010</cite>. Such vehicles, whether registered for a full period or part thereof and whether or not previously registered, shall be registered at the full fee. If a person authorized to register a vehicle at a fee of $5 under <cite path="§VEH.3.8.010">Section VEH.3.8.010</cite> transfers the vehicle to a person not so authorized, the fee payable by the transferee shall be computed as for a vehicle not previously registered by the Lac Courte Oreilles.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The credit or plate transfer provisions authorized under <cite path="§VEH.3.11.030">this section</cite> do not apply if the applicant has, within the preceding 12 months, transferred or received credit for registration plates removed from the motor vehicle which is the subject of the application.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.030 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.37</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.040</num>
        <heading>Re-Registration Required for Vehicles Subject to a Different Fee</heading>
        <text>Whenever the construction or the use of a registered vehicle is changed in a manner making the vehicle subject to a different registration fee than the fee for which the vehicle currently is registered, the owner shall immediately make application for registration. The fee payable upon such re-registration shall be computed as for a vehicle not previously registered in this jurisdiction but a credit shall be allowed for the unused portion of the fee paid for the previous registration if the registration plates issued upon the previous registration are returned to the department. The credit shall be computed on the basis of one-twelfth of the annual registration fee or one twenty-fourth of the biennial registration fee prescribed for the vehicle as previously registered multiplied by the number of months of registration which have not fully expired on the date the vehicle became subject to the different fee. The credit may be applied toward the reregistration of the vehicle only up to the date when the previous registration would have expired.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.040 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.38</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.050</num>
        <heading>Refundable Fees</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The department shall not refund a fee paid to it except when expressly authorized or directed by <cite path="§VEH.3.11.050">this section</cite> or some other provision of this ordinance to do so.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon request, the department shall refund 50 percent of a registration fee paid for a vehicle registered on a biennial basis if the person who registered the vehicle furnishes such proof as the department requires that the person has transferred his or her interest in the vehicle before the beginning of the second year of the period for which the vehicle is registered or that the vehicle will not be operated within the jurisdiction of the Lac Courte Oreilles after the beginning of the second year of the period for which the vehicle is registered. The department may require the person to return the certificate of registration and registration plates for the vehicle to the department.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.050 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.39</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.060</num>
        <heading>Change of Address</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whenever any person, after applying for and receiving registration plates, moves from the address named in the application for the registration plates or when the name of the licensee is changed by marriage or otherwise, the person shall within 10 days notify the department in writing of the old and new address or of such former and new names and of all registration plate numbers held.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any person who fails to comply with any of the requirements of par. (a) may be required to forfeit not more than $25.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.060 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.40</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.070</num>
        <heading>Reinstatement of Suspended or Revoked Registration</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in par. (b), the department shall charge a fee of $25 to reinstate a registration previously suspended or revoked under this law. The fee under this subsection is in addition to any other fee required to complete the registration of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Par. (a) does not apply to the reinstatement of a registration suspended or revoked as a result of an error by the department.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.070 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.41</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.080</num>
        <heading>Exemption of Nonresidents and Foreign Registered Vehicles</heading>
        <text>Any vehicle which is registered in another jurisdiction is exempt from the Lac Courte Oreilles Motor Vehicle Registration Ordinance providing for the registration of such vehicles if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The vehicle carries a registration plate indicating the registration in such other jurisdiction, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The vehicle is owned by a nonresident of the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the owner of such vehicle moves within the jurisdiction Lac Courte Oreilles or if the vehicle is purchased by a Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal member, the vehicle immediately becomes subject to the laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles providing for registration of vehicles.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.080 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.42</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.11.090</num>
        <heading>Reciprocal Agreements</heading>
        <text>The Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians may enter into a reciprocal exemption agreement with the State of Wisconsin. The reciprocal agreement may exempt designated classes of vehicles registered by the department from the registration requirements of the State of Wisconsin.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.11.090 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.43</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.12</num>
      <heading>Penalties</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.12.010</num>
        <heading>Fraudulent Applications</heading>
        <text>Any person who gives a false or fictitious name, address or location where a vehicle is customarily kept in an application for license or registration or who makes application for license or registration in the name of a person other than the true owner, or true owner and lessee, may be fined not more than $200.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.12.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.44</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.12.020</num>
        <heading>Improper Use of Evidence of Registration</heading>
        <text>Any person who does any of the following may be subject to a fine of not more than $500:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Lends to another a registration plate for display upon a vehicle for which the plate has not been issued.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Displays upon a vehicle a registration plate not issued for such vehicle or not otherwise authorized by law to be used thereon.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Willfully twists, paints, alters or adds to or cuts off any portion of a registration plate or sticker; or who places or deposits, or causes to be placed or deposited on such plate or sticker any substance to hinder the normal reading or such plate; or who defaces, disfigures, covers, obstruct, changes or attempts to change any letter or figure thereon; or who causes such plate or sticker to appear to be a different color.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.12.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.45</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.12.030</num>
        <heading>Special Registration Plates</heading>
        <text>Any person who fraudulently procures or uses special registration plates issued under <cite path="§VEH.3.2.030">Section VEH.3.2.030</cite> of this ordinance shall forfeit not less than $200, nor more than $500.</text>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.12.030 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.46</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.13</num>
      <heading>When Registration Is to Be Suspended</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.13.010</num>
        <heading>When Suspended</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The department shall suspend the registration of a vehicle when:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The registration was completed through fraud or error and the person who registered the vehicle does not or cannot register the vehicle properly.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The required fee has not been paid and the same is not paid upon reasonable notice and demand.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Suspension of registration is specified by an authority under <cite path="§VEH.3.14.010">Section VEH.3.14.010</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The applicant fails, upon reasonable notice and demand, to furnish proof of payment, in the form prescribed by the U.S. Secretary of Treasury, that the federal heavy vehicle use tax imposed by section 4481 of the Internal Revenue Code has been paid.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The licensee of a vehicle registered under <cite path="§VEH.3.7.010">Section VEH.3.7.010</cite> has not been compiled with the test or inspection requirements of the State of Wisconsin under <cite path="s|s.110|s.110.20">s.110.20</cite>(6)Wis. Stats.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any registration suspended pursuant to <cite path="§VEH.3.13.010">this section</cite> continues to be suspended until reinstated by the department. The department shall reinstate the registration when the reason for the suspension has been removed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whenever the registration of a vehicle is suspended under <cite path="§VEH.3.13.010">this section</cite>, the department may order the owner or person in possession of the registration plates to return them to the department. Any person who fails to return the plates when ordered to do so by the department may be required to forfeit not more than $200.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.13.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.47</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.13.020</num>
        <heading>Transfer of Vehicle Ownership While Registration Suspended</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>No owner may transfer the ownership or registration of any vehicle whose registration is suspended under <cite path="§VEH.3.13.010">Section VEH.3.13.010</cite> until the registration is reinstated under <cite path="§VEH.3.13.010|(b)">Section VEH.3.13.010(b)</cite> or until the department is satisfied that such transfer is proposed in good faith and not for the purpose or with the effect of defeating the purposes of <cite path="§VEH.3.13.010|(a)|(3)">Section VEH.3.13.010(a)(3)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any person violating <cite path="§VEH.3.13.020">this section</cite> may be subject to a fine of not more than $200.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><cite path="§VEH.3.13.020">This section</cite> does not apply to or affect the registration of any vehicle sold by a person who, pursuant to the terms or conditions of any written instrument giving a right of repossession, has exercised such right and has repossessed such vehicle from a person who registration has been suspended under <cite path="§VEH.3.13.010|(a)|(3)">Section VEH.3.13.010(a)(3)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.13.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.48</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <num>VEH.3.14</num>
      <heading>Nonmoving Violations</heading>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.14.010</num>
        <heading>Non-Moving Violation</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As used in <cite path="§VEH.3.14.010">this section</cite>:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>"Authority" means a Tribal Authority<em>,</em> a local authority, or a state agency.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>"Forfeiture" includes a fine established under this ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>"Nonmoving traffic violation" is any parking of a vehicle in violation of a statute, an ordinance, or a resolution of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians or the State of Wisconsin.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the person does not pay the forfeiture or appear in court in response to the citation for a nonmoving traffic violation on the date specified in the citation or, if no date is specified in the citation, within 28 days after the citation is issued, the authority which issued the citation may issue a summons to the person and, in lieu of or in addition to issuing the summons, may proceed but, except as provided in <cite path="§VEH.3.14.010">this section</cite>, no warrant may be issued for the person. If the person appears in response to a summons for a nonmoving traffic violation, the procedures under the current Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court rules and regulations shall apply.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the person does not pay the forfeiture or appear in court in response to the citation for a nonmoving traffic violation on the date specified in the citation or, if no date is specified in the citation, within 28 days after the citation is issued, the authority may notify the department in the form and manner prescribed by the department that a citation has been issued to the person and the citation remains unpaid. The authority shall specify whether the department is to suspend the registration of the vehicle involved under <cite path="§VEH.3.13.010">Section VEH.3.13.010</cite> or refuse registration of any vehicle owned by the person.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.14.010 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.49</annotation>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>VEH.3.14.020</num>
        <heading>Penalty for Operating Unregistered or Improperly Registered Vehicle</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to operate or for an owner to consent to being</text>
          <text>operated on any highway of this jurisdiction any motor vehicle, mobile home, trailer, or any other vehicle for which a registration fee is specifically prescribed unless at the time of operation the vehicle in question either is registered in this jurisdiction, or, a complete application for registration, including evidence of any inspection required by the jurisdiction, accompanied by the required fee has been delivered to the department or deposited in the mail properly addressed with postage prepaid, and if the vehicle is an automobile, station wagon or motor truck having a registered weight of 8,000 pounds or less, the vehicle displays a temporary operation plate issued for the vehicle unless the operator or owner of the vehicle displays a temporary operation plate issued for the vehicle unless the operator or owner of the vehicle produces proof that operation of the vehicle is within 2 business days of the vehicle's sale or transfer, or the vehicle in question is exempt from registration.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A vehicle may be operated by a private person after the date of purchase of such vehicle by such private person or after the date such person moved to this jurisdiction if application for registration and certificate of title has been made.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All vehicles subject to renewal or registration may be operated provided that application for re-registration has been made.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Unless application for re-registration has been made as required by <cite path="§VEH.3.11.040">Section VEH.3.11.040</cite>, it is unlawful for any person to operate or for the owner to consent to being operated on any highway of this jurisdiction any registered vehicle the construction or use of which has been changed so as to make the vehicle subject to a higher fee than the fee at which it currently is registered or which is carrying a greater load than that permitted under the current registration.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any person who violates par. (a) or (b), where the vehicle used is an automobile, station wagon, or any other vehicle having a gross weight of 10,000 pounds or less, may be required to forfeit not more than $200.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any person who violates par. (a) or (b), where the vehicle used is vehicle not enumerated under sub. (1), may be required to forfeit not more than $500.</text>
        </para>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§VEH.3.14.020 was formerly codified as LCOTCC §5.50</annotation>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
</container>
