<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>VII-3</num>
  <heading>Guardianship Of Adults And Protective Placement Code Of The Lac Courte Oreilles Band Of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</heading>
  <text class="center"><strong>Preamble</strong></text>
  <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, Article V, § 1 (s), (t), and (u) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians empowers the Tribal Governing Board to "promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and providing for the maintenance of law and order and the administration of justice …" Article V, § 1 (s); "provide for the regulation of … domestic relations matters by ordinances or resolution" Article V, § 1 (t); "provide for the appointment of guardians for … mental incompetents by ordinance or resolution" Article V, § 1 (u). The Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians recognizes the need to promote the traditional value of respect for adults in need of protective placement or guardianship. The Tribe recognizes that adults that suffer from physical or mental disability, incapacity, other disability, or are substantially impaired whether from age, disease, alcohol, substance abuse, or psychological problems all deserve to lead a life of safety and respect. The dignity, self-reliance and rights of adults in need of protective placement or guardianship must be respected by family members, the Tribal community, employees of the Tribe and all people who are part of or inter-act with the Tribe and its adults in need of protective placement or guardianship. It is the purpose of this ordinance to protect the health, safety and welfare of all persons within the jurisdiction of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe and to codify a process and procedure governing the appointment of a Guardian for Adults who are incapable of managing their own affairs, require assistance in conducting business, or require assistance in obtaining necessary services. Thus, it is in the best interest of and serves the welfare of the Tribe to protect adults in need of protective placement or guardianship.</text>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>3.1</num>
    <heading>Introduction</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.101</num>
      <heading>Title</heading>
      <text>This ordinance shall be known as the Guardianship of Adults and Protective Placement Code of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians (hereinafter "Tribe").</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.102</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, Article V, § 1 (s), (t), and (u) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians empowers the Tribal Governing Board to "promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and providing for the maintenance of law and order and the administration of justice …" Article V, § 1 (s); "provide for the regulation of … domestic relations matters by ordinances or resolution" Article V, § 1 (t); "provide for the appointment of guardians for … mental incompetents by ordinance or resolution" Article V, § 1 (u).</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.103</num>
      <heading>Policy</heading>
      <text>It is the policy of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe to promote the traditional value of respect for adults in need of protective placement or guardianship. The Tribe recognizes that adults that suffer from physical or mental disability, incapacity, other disability, or are substantially impaired whether from age, disease, alcohol, substance abuse, or psychological problems all deserve to lead a life of safety and respect. The dignity, self-reliance and rights of adults in need of protective placement or guardianship must be respected by family members, the Tribal community, employees of the Tribe and all people who are part of or inter-act with the Tribe and its adults in need of protective placement or guardianship. Thus, it is in the best interest of and serves the welfare of the Tribe to protect adults in need of protective placement or guardianship.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>It is the purpose of this ordinance to protect the health, safety and welfare of all persons within the jurisdiction of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe and to codify a process and procedure governing the appointment of a Guardian for Adults who are incapable of managing their own affairs, require assistance in conducting business, or require assistance in obtaining necessary services.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.105</num>
      <heading>Effective Date</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this ordinance shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.106</num>
      <heading>Interpretation</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this ordinance:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be interpreted and applied as minimum requirements applicable to promote and protect the well-being of the person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be used to encourage the development of maximum self-reliance and independence of the person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall be utilized only to the extent necessitated by the person's actual mental and physical limitations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Does not waive the sovereign immunity of the Tribe in any respect.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.107</num>
      <heading>Severability And Non-Liability</heading>
      <text>If any section, provision or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this ordinance.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108</num>
      <heading>Repeal Of Inconsistent Tribal Ordinances</heading>
      <text>All ordinances and resolutions inconsistent with this ordinance are hereby repealed. To the extent that this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, code, ordinance or regulation, the provisions of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>3.2</num>
    <heading>Definitions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.201</num>
      <heading>General Definitions</heading>
      <text>Any term not defined in this Section shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><strong>"Guardian"</strong> means an individual who is appointed by any Court to manage the income and assets and provide for the essential requirements and safety and the personal needs of an individual found to be incompetent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><strong>"Guardian ad Litem"</strong> means an individual who is appointed by the Court to represent the best interests of the proposed ward;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text><strong>"Incapacity" </strong>means the current functional inability of a person to sufficiently understand, make, and communicate responsible decisions about him/herself as a result of mental illness, mental deficiency, physical illness or disability, or chronic use of drugs or alcohol, and to understand the consequences of any such decision. Incapacity may vary in degree and duration and shall not be determined solely on the basis of age.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text><strong>"Person"</strong> means a proposed ward who is a member of the Tribe or is eligible for membership in the Tribe, whether or not domiciled on the Reservation, or an Indian person who resides within the boundaries of the Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text><strong>"Proposed Ward"</strong> means a person alleged to be incapacitated for whom a petition for guardianship is filed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text><strong>"Protective Placement"</strong> means the placement of an individual found to be incapacitated in a hospital, nursing home, residential care facility, or transfer of the individual found to be incapacitated from one such institution to another with appropriate legal authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text><strong>"Protective Services" </strong>means the services provided to an individual found to be incapacitated which include, but are not limited to: social case work, psychiatric and health evaluation, home care, day care, legal assistance, social services, health care, case management, guardianship and other services consistent with this ordinance. It does not include protective placement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text><strong>"Reservation"</strong> means lands located within the exterior boundaries of the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation lands as well as off-reservation lands under the jurisdiction and purview of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text><strong>"Tribal Court"</strong> means the duly constituted court of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, as established by the Tribal Governing Board, with the judicial authority of the Tribe pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution 76-10, dated May 27, 1976.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text><strong>"Tribe"</strong> means the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>3.3</num>
    <heading>Jurisdiction</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.301</num>
      <heading>Jurisdiction</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Court shall have jurisdiction over all petitions for adult guardianship over the person or estate of a person alleged to be incapacitated who is a member of the Tribe or is eligible for membership in the Tribe, whether or not domiciled on the Reservation, or an Indian person who resides within the boundaries of the Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the Court exercise jurisdiction over any Indian person who is not a member of the Tribe but who is a member of another tribe, the Court shall verify that notice was given to such other tribe, and an opportunity to participate as a witness, to intervene as a party, or to file a motion seeking transfer of proceedings to the other Tribe's Court shall be permitted. If a person's Tribe objects to the jurisdiction of the Court prior to entry of a final judgment in the case, the Court shall waive jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>3.4</num>
    <heading>Adult Guardianships</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.401</num>
      <heading>Types Of Adult Guardianships</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Court may appoint a guardian on a temporary or permanent basis, under the procedures established by this subchapter. The Court may appoint a special guardian to perform a specific task or tasks.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.402</num>
      <heading>Temporary Adult Guardianship</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A temporary adult guardianship shall not exceed 30 days, unless extended by the judge or magistrate for one additional period of 30 days, upon a petition and affidavit showing grounds for the appointment of a guardian.  Any individual appointed temporary guardian shall post a bond in the amount required by the judge or magistrate. An order appointing a temporary guardian may be granted without hearing, notice, or appointment of a guardian ad litem.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.403</num>
      <heading>Duties And Powers Of Guardians</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Court may appoint a guardian of the person and a guardian of the estate of any person. An individual may serve as both guardian of the person and guardian of the estate, or different individuals may be appointed. Joint guardians may be appointed of either the person or the estate or both, provided that the joint guardians shall have joint and several liability for acts undertaken as guardian by either of them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A guardian of the person shall make all decisions for the ward and may act in the place of the ward, except that the guardian of the person may not act for, bind, or appear in any legal action affecting the property of the person. The guardian of the person may consent or refuse consent to medical treatment on behalf of the ward. The guardian of the person may consent to the admission of the ward to any residential facility for the care or treatment of the ward, including but not limited to a hospital or other medical facility, nursing home, community based residential facility, or psychiatric facility, for no more than 90 days without a protective placement order under § 3.602.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A guardian of the person may not consent or refuse to consent to the administration of psychotropic medication to the ward unless specifically granted the authority by the Court in the guardianship order.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A guardian of the person is exempt from civil liability for acts or omissions in the performance of the duties of guardianship if the guardian acts in good faith and with the same ordinary diligence and prudence that a reasonable individual would take in the conduct of one's own affairs. This exemption from liability does not apply to any guardian of the estate who commits waste, fraud, or negligent mismanagement as to the estate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A guardian of the estate shall manage the assets, income, and financial interests of the ward for the benefit of the ward. A guardian of the estate may not sell any interest in the ward's real estate without the specific approval of the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>No guardian shall lend or give any funds or other property of the ward or ward's estate to himself or herself. No guardian shall purchase any property of the ward unless for fair market value and with specific approval of the Court.</text>
        <text>
          <u>SUBCHAPTER 3.5 – Adult Guardianship PROCEDURES</u>
        </text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.501</num>
      <heading>Who May Petition For Adult Guardianship</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any individual may petition for guardianship of a proposed ward.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.502</num>
      <heading>Petition</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The petition for adult guardianship shall contain the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name, residence, address, post office address, date of birth, and tribal membership status of the proposed ward, the petitioner, and of the proposed guardian or guardians.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The reason guardianship is sought.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Whether temporary or permanent guardianship is sought.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Whether a guardian of the person or a guardian of the estate or both is sought.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The income and assets of the proposed ward.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Whether any guardian of the proposed ward now exists.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Whether the authority to consent or refuse consent to psychotropic medication under § 3.506 (4) is requested.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Whether protective placement under § 3.602 is sought.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.503</num>
      <heading>Guardian Ad Litem</heading>
      <text>Upon receipt of a petition under § 3.502, the Court shall appoint a guardian ad litem for the proposed ward. The guardian ad litem shall have the right and obligation to interview the proposed ward, the petitioner, and the proposed guardian or guardians, and others as appropriate; and to review medical or other records as appropriate, and to present evidence at the hearing under § 3.506, and to make recommendations to the Court as to the petition.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.504</num>
      <heading>Notice</heading>
      <text>A copy of the petition and of a notice of hearing shall be provided to the proposed ward,</text>
      <text>to any current guardian of the proposed ward, to the guardian ad litem of the proposed ward, and to any spouse, parent, or adult child of the proposed ward, unless the Court orders for a specific reason that notice need not to be given to any such person. Notice may be given by any means allowed under 2 LCOTCL § 1.902, no less than ten days before the hearing under § 3.506.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.505</num>
      <heading>Physician'S Or Psychologist'S Report</heading>
      <text>No guardian shall be appointed based on any alleged mental incapacity of the proposed ward to manage the proposed ward's own affairs without the testimony of a licensed physician or psychologist. Upon stipulation of all the parties, a written report of a licensed physician or psychologist may be introduced in lieu of testimony.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.506</num>
      <heading>Guardianship Hearing And Order</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the hearing on the petition, the Court shall hear the petitioner's evidence, the evidence offered by any other party, and the recommendations of the guardian ad litem. If the Court is satisfied by clear and convincing evidence that the proposed ward is incapable of managing his or her own affairs and that the appointment of a guardian is in the best interests of the proposed ward, the Court shall appoint a guardian or guardians who by a preponderance of the evidence, appears most suitable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Court may impose restrictions or limitations on the powers of the guardian, and may condition the appointment on the guardian's performance of specified duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Court shall determine whether all of the ward's rights shall be exercised by the guardian, or whether the ward shall retain the right to exercise any particular rights.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Court shall make specific findings and orders with respect to any request for authority to consent or refuse consent to psychotropic medications. A guardian seeking such authority must prove by clear and convincing evidence the following;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That the proposed ward is likely to respond positively to psychotropic medication.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That as a result of the proposed ward's failure to take medication the person is unable to provide for his or her care in the community. The proposed ward's past history is relevant to determining his or her current inability to provide for his or her care in the community under this paragraph.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>That unless protective services, including psychotropic medication, are provided, the proposed ward will incur a substantial probability of physical harm, impairment, injury or debilitation or will present a substantial probability of physical harm to others.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Court shall make specific findings and orders with respect to a request for protective placement.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.507</num>
      <heading>Bond</heading>
      <text>The Court may require any guardian to post a bond as security that the guardian will faithfully perform the duties of such office.  The Court may accept a signature bond.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.508</num>
      <heading>Standards For Determining Incapacity</heading>
      <text>No finding that a ward is incapable of managing his or her own affairs may be based on physical incapacity alone. A finding that a ward is incapable of managing his or her own affairs may be based on development disabilities; degeneration of the brain associated with aging; or organic brain damage, defect, or injury. Such a finding may also be based on inability to care for oneself based on serious and sustained abuse of alcohol or other drugs. Such a finding may also be based on the proposed ward's inability to control income and assets such as to the subject the proposed ward to risk of exploitation by others, or to endanger the health, life, or property of the proposed ward.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.509</num>
      <heading>Inventory</heading>
      <text>Any person appointed guardian of the estate shall complete, under oath, an inventory of all the ward's property within thirty (30) days of appointment, on forms supplied by the Clerk of Court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.510</num>
      <heading>Annual Report</heading>
      <text>Any person appointed guardian of the estate shall each year complete, under oath, a report showing the ward's assets, liabilities, income, and expenses for the period of the report, on forms supplied by the Clerk of Court.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.511</num>
      <heading>Change Of Address</heading>
      <text>Any guardian of the person or the estate shall notify the Clerk of Court within ten (10) days of any change of address or the guardian of the ward.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>3.6</num>
    <heading>Protective Placement</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.601</num>
      <heading>Order</heading>
      <text>Protective placement is a court order specifying the location and conditions of the ward's residence. No person may be found to be in need of protective placement unless subject to a guardianship ordered under Subchapter 3.5</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.602</num>
      <heading>Request For Protective Placement</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A request for protective placement shall be combined with a guardianship petition under Subchapter 3.5, unless a guardianship has already been created, in which case, the petition shall so state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the petitioner seeks protective placement for the ward, the petition shall allege, and the petitioner shall prove by clear and convincing evidence the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The ward has a primary need for residential care and custody.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a result of developmental disabilities, infirmities of aging, chronic mental illness or other like incapacities, the ward is so totally incapable of providing for his or her own care or custody as to create a substantial risk of serious harm to oneself or others.  Serious harm may be occasioned by over acts of omission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The ward has a disability which is permanent or likely to be permanent.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The physician's or psychologist's report required under § 3.506 shall also address the requirements listed in subs. (2), above in any case where protective placement is sought.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the Court orders a protective placement, it shall protectively place the ward in the least restrictive residential setting consistent with the needs of the ward.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.603</num>
      <heading>Annual Review</heading>
      <text>No less than once each twelve (12) months, the Court shall order an annual review of any protective placement, to determine if the conditions justifying the protective placement still exist:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Court shall appoint a guardian ad litem in a timely fashion to allow the guardian ad litem to complete his or tasks as set forth in subs. (2), below prior to the completion of the twelve (12) month period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The guardian ad litem shall meet with the ward, talk to the guardian, and review the medical records of the ward and the records of any facility providing the ward's residential care.  The guardian ad litem shall inform the ward of the purpose of the annual review, shall determine, if possible, whether the ward wishes a hearing on the continued protective placement. The guardian ad litem shall report his or her findings and recommendations to the Court no later than fifteen (15) days before the completion of the twelve (12) month period, on forms prescribed by the Clerk of Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If neither the ward, guardian, guardian ad litem, nor any other person requests a hearing, and if the guardian ad litem recommends continuation of the protective placement, then the Court may either hold a hearing on the continuation of the protective placement, or may order a twelve (12) month continuation of the protective placement based on the reports in the record.</text>
        <text>
          <u>SUBCHAPTER 3.7 – termination or changes</u>
        </text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.701</num>
      <heading>Termination Or Changes To An Order For Adult Guardianship</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon motion and hearing, with notice to the guardian and ward, and appointment of a guardian ad litem, the Court may remove the guardian and a successor guardian may be appointed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the guardian neglects to perform any action required by law or by the Court;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the guardian fails to discharge the duties of guardianship;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the guardian acts contrary to the interests of the ward;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If the guardian violates any provision of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon motion and hearing, with notice to the guardian and ward, and appointment of a guardian ad litem, a guardianship may be terminated if by clear and convincing evidence it is established that the conditions requiring the guardianship no longer exist.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.702</num>
      <heading>Termination Or Changes To An Order For Adult Protective Placement</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon motion and hearing, with notice to the guardian and ward, and appointment of a guardian ad litem, a protective placement may be changed or terminated if by clear and convincing evidence it is established that the conditions requiring the protective placement no longer exist.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
