<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>XIV-17</num>
  <heading>Big Fish Golf Corporation Personnel Policies And Procedures</heading>
  <text>Preamble</text>
  <text>The Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians (hereinafter "Band" or "Tribe") in an effort to diversify the economy of the Tribe's reservation in order to improve the Tribe's economic self-sufficiency petitioned the Secretary of the Interior to issue a charter of corporation pursuant to section 17 of the Indian Reorganization Act, codified at U.S.C. § 5124. The BIA – Midwest Regional Office issued a certificate of incorporation for the Big Fish Golf Corporation (hereinafter "Big Fish Golf Corp" or "BFGC"). Big Fish Golf Corp is a legal entity wholly owned by the Tribe, but distinct and separate from the Tribe.</text>
  <text>This personnel policy and procedural manual is enacted pursuant to the management authority of the Board of Directors of the Big Fish Golf Corp. This personnel and procedure manual outlines the general policies, rules and procedures and is intended to be a helpful reference during your employment with the BFGC. The information contained herein is general information, and its contents do not create or constitute a contract between BFGC and any employee. The Board of Directors acting in its management capacity may in its sole discretion amend this personnel policy and procedural manual from time to time.</text>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.1</num>
    <heading>General Provisions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.101</num>
      <heading>Title</heading>
      <text>This personnel policies and procedures manual shall be known as the Big Fish Golf Corporation (BFGC) Personnel Policies and Procedures.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.102</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <text>This personnel policy and procedural manual is enacted pursuant to Article XI, Sec. A. of the Federal Charter of Incorporation issued by the United States of America to the Tribe for Big Fish Golf Corporation. Pursuant to Article XI, Sec. A., the business affairs of the Big Fish Golf Corporation shall be managed exclusively by its Board of Directors.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.103</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>It is the purpose of this personnel policy and procedural manual to provide the general policies, rules and procedures of BFGC. This personnel policy and procedural manual is intended to govern your employment with the BFGC. The information contained herein is general information, and its contents do not create or constitute a contract between BFGC and any employee. Nothing can take the place of direct communication. If you have any questions concerning the applicability of a policy or practice, you should address your concerns to your supervisor.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.104</num>
      <heading>Mission Statement</heading>
      <text>We are dedicated to making our guests feel delighted to be at the Big Fish Golf Club and to feel completely comfortable by using a friendly, upbeat manner and by providing them with cheerful and prompt service, excellent product and clean, well-kept facilities.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.105</num>
      <heading>Big Fish Golf Corporation Core Values</heading>
      <text>Our product is <strong><em>hospitality</em></strong>. Our guests can golf anywhere. We will deliver the best quality service possible. We are a team. We are a united front. We all look good together or we all look bad together. We treat each other and guests with the utmost respect and courtesy. There are no problems, only challenges. We will take ownership of any guest issues. We will never tell a guest, that's not my department. Hospitality is a way of being. It is not an option. We are on stage and must act the part at all times of an enthusiastic and willing service provider. We are committed to growth as a business, as team members and as individuals.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.106</num>
      <heading>Effective Date</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this personnel policy and procedural manual shall be effective on the date adopted by the Big Fish Golf Corporation Board of Directors.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.107</num>
      <heading>Interpretation</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this personnel policy and procedural manual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be interpreted and applied as minimum requirements applicable to the employment related activities of the BFGC;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of BFGC;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.108</num>
      <heading>Severability And Non-Liability</heading>
      <text>If any section, provision or portion of this personnel policy and procedural manual is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this personnel policy and procedural manual shall not be affected thereby. Pursuant to Article XIV, Sec. A., the Big Fish Golf Corp. is an instrumentality of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin, and consistent with Article IV, is entitled to all of the privileges and immunities of the Tribe, except as provided in Article XIV.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.2</num>
    <heading>Definitions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.201</num>
      <heading>General Definitions</heading>
      <text>Any term not defined in this section shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><strong>"Contracted Employee"</strong> means an employee who has entered into a written contract, which has been properly authorized and signed by a signatory of the BFGC Board of Directors and the employee which defines the employment relationship. The contract will be for a specified period, and will outline benefits, pay and other conditions of employment. The terms and conditions of employment for Contracted employees may differ from the terms in this personnel policy and procedural manual, and this manual may be incorporated by reference in the Contracted Employee's written contract.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><strong>"Employee" </strong>means an employee of the BFGC including:  Exempt Employee, Non-exempt Employee, Full-time Employee, Seasonal Employee, or Temporary Employee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text><strong>"Independent contractor"</strong> means an individual who is not an employee of the BFGC, but rather has entered into a contract with the BFGC, which defines the scope of services. Independent contractors are not employees, do not receive benefits, are not subject to this personnel policy and procedural manual and are governed by a written or verbal contract.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text><strong>"Management" </strong>means the General Manager, Director of Golf, Office Manager and any employee who is assigned permanent or temporary supervisory or decision-making authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text><strong>"Non-Exempt Employee"</strong> means an employee who the Human Resources designee, categorizes as being non-exempt from accruing compensatory time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text><strong>"Part-time Employee"</strong> means an employee regularly scheduled to work less than thirty-two (32) hours per week. Part-time employees are not eligible for employee benefits or leave.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text><strong>"Positive Test Result"</strong> means a Blood Alcohol Concentration determined to be under the influence as established in § 17.201 (10) and 17.805 (3).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text><strong>"Seasonal Employee"</strong> means an employee hired for an established period usually during peak workloads or seasonal demands. Seasonal workers may not be eligible for all employee benefits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text><strong>"Temporary Employee"</strong> means an employee hired for a period of ninety (90) days or less. Temporary employees may work a full-time or part-time schedule and are not eligible for employee benefits and paid leave.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text><strong>"Under the Influence of Alcohol</strong>, <strong>Illegal Drugs or Controlled Substances"</strong> means the following: a Blood Alcohol Concentration that indicates a positive test result as established in § 17.805 (3); or are results that confirm the presence of illegal substance; or are results that confirm the presence of a controlled substances that an employee does not have a valid prescription for or the levels exceed the prescribed dosage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text><strong>"Valid Prescription"</strong> means a prescription that is current and issued for a medical purpose in the usual course of professional practice by a practitioner or a covering practitioner who has conducted at least 1 in-person medical evaluation of the patient.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.3</num>
    <heading>Governance</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.301</num>
      <heading>General</heading>
      <text>The BFGC is owned solely by the Tribe for the benefit of the Tribe and its recognized citizens. The Tribal Governing Board is the Member's representative, and all rights of the Member shall be exercised by the Tribal Governing Board, in accordance with the Federal Charter of Incorporation issued by the United States of America to the Tribe for Big Fish Golf Corporation and applicable tribal law. The Tribal Governing Board in their capacity possess the inherent sovereign authority to delegate oversight and management responsibilities to program directors for the planning and daily operations of Tribal programs and entities. Pursuant to Article XI, Sec. A., the business affairs of the Big Fish Golf Corporation shall be managed exclusively by its Board of Directors. The Tribal Court interprets and enforces, in accordance with and subject to applicable law, as well as these policies and procedures established by the BFGC Board of Directors.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.302</num>
      <heading>Sovereignty</heading>
      <text>The Tribe is a sovereign nation, with inherent reserved rights recognized through federal treaties; as such the tribe exists within the geographical boundaries of the United States. Pursuant to Article XIV, Sec. A., the BFGC is an instrumentality of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin, and consistent with Article IV, is entitled to all the privileges and immunities of the Tribe, except as provided in Article XIV. Immunity from private lawsuits is one aspect of inherent tribal sovereignty. Immunity from suit means that no private lawsuit can be maintained against the BFGC unless the BFGC Board of Directors consents to the action. Nothing in this manual, constitutes a waiver of the BFGC's inherent sovereign immunity.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.303</num>
      <heading>Employment Laws</heading>
      <text>It is the general policy of the BFGC to extend to its employees, where possible, the rights and benefits provided by employers regulated by the laws of the United States. However, the BFGC looks to federal employment laws as guidelines only, and nothing in this personnel policy and procedural manual shall be construed as the BFGC's consent to application of such laws. Another aspect of BFGC's inherent sovereignty is that Wisconsin Statutes are not applicable to the operations of the BFGC without the express written permission of the Big Fish Golf Corp. The Tribe reserves the right to create and modify its employment laws and policies without regard to such laws or interpretations thereof.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.4</num>
    <heading>Hiring Process</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.401</num>
      <heading>Equal Employment Opportunity</heading>
      <text>The BFGC is committed to equal employment opportunity and advancement toward all applicants and employees regardless of race, color, creed, national origin, gender, sexual orientation, marital status, veteran status, religion, status with regard to public assistance, disability, age or any other status protected by law.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.402</num>
      <heading>Indian Preference</heading>
      <text>The BFGC grants Indian preference in employment, and will apply preference in the following order when there are two or more candidates that meet the job qualifications:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Members of other Federally Recognized Tribes with a dependent or dependents who are members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Members of other Federally Recognized Tribes,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Non-members with a dependent or dependents who are members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All Others.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.403</num>
      <heading>Hiring Preferences</heading>
      <text>The BFGC will utilize the following preference ranking when considering an applicant for employment. It is the responsibility of the applicant to provide the necessary documents listed below for the purpose of obtaining preferences:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Indian preference as described in § 17.402 of this manual (Applicant must provide a signed official document from a federally recognized Tribe acknowledging enrollment);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Veteran preference (Applicant must provide a Veterans Administration form DD214);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Former employees of the BFGC who left in "good standing" and whose separation was not as a result of disciplinary action or an agreement in lieu of disciplinary action which would have otherwise resulted in termination.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.404</num>
      <heading>Employment Of Minors</heading>
      <text>The BFGC Corporation will utilize, solely as a guideline, federal laws pertaining to the employment of minors.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.405</num>
      <heading>Posting</heading>
      <text>The Human Resources designee will advertise all job postings locally at various locations and other places as appropriate including electronic posting.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.406</num>
      <heading>Job Application</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><u>Application Form</u>. Applicants for employment are required to submit an application form.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.407</num>
      <heading>Screening And Selection Process</heading>
      <text>As an employer, the BFGC seeks to employ individuals who possess the qualifications, skills, abilities and background to meet the employment needs of the BFGC. It is also the intent of the BFGC to treat all applicants with respect and fairness along with ensuring the provisions of § 17.401 of this manual, are adhered to. Pursuant to the Privacy Act of 1974, 5 U.S.C. § 552a, all applications shall be treated as privileged information and shall be made available only to those directly involved in the hiring process.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><u>Applicant Screening</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon receipt, all applications will be date stamped and kept in the hiring file. All applications received, within the required time lines, will be reviewed by the Human Resources designee for completeness and minimum qualifications.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Applicants that are deemed to meet the minimum qualifications will be notified of an offer to be interviewed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The decision to not offer an interview will not be subject to any grievance, complaint or appeal provisions.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In the event management determines that there are no qualified or insufficient applicants the position may be reposted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Reference and background checks made by the Human Resources designee should be properly documented and retained for a period no longer than the probationary period of the position being considered.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><u>Applicant Interview</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All eligible applicants will be interviewed by a committee which may dependent on the position be comprised of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Human Resources Designee, and/or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Management, and/or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Other Employees as Management deems appropriate.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text><u>Interviewing Principles</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The committee will interview each eligible applicant and shall make the selection based upon all relevant factors, including but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Preferences defined in § 17.403 of this manual,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Education/Training,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Personal and professional references,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Experience relevant to position,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Interview.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The committee may utilize a ranking system that factors all of the areas established in subsection (3) (a) above, that will ensure a fair and equitable process for determining the best qualified candidate, and if applicable an alternate, to fill the position being interviewed. Such system may utilize points or other forms of ranking that is deemed relevant for the position in consideration. The Human Resources designee shall forward the committee's recommendation to management for review and approval.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Human Resources designee shall notify the successful and unsuccessful applicants in writing within five (5) working days.  If the selected individual does not accept the position or an employee does not successfully complete the probationary period, the Human Resources designee shall offer the position to the alternate selection, if applicable.  If there was no alternate selected, then the Human Resources designee may repost the position as approved by management.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All relevant documents related to a hiring will be retained by the Human Resources designee for a period not longer than the probationary period for the position being considered. Pursuant to the Privacy Act of 1974, 5 U.S.C. § 552a, all such information shall be treated as privileged information and shall be made available only to those directly involved in the hiring process.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>If an employee does not complete the probationary period, the Human Resources designee shall offer the position to the alternate selection. If there was no alternate selected, then the Human Resources designee may repost the position as approved by management.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The decision to not hire an interviewee will not be subject to any grievance, complaint or appeal provisions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.408</num>
      <heading>Orientation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All new employees will be provided an orientation and will be provided this personnel policy and procedural manual and all required forms for employment. The Human Resources designee will also answer any questions which may arise throughout the course of employment.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.409</num>
      <heading>Position Description</heading>
      <text>The Human Resources designee, will provide every employee with a copy of his or her current and or amended position description. The position description is intended to provide a general overview of the duties of the position. From time to time, however, employees will perform duties and handle duties and responsibilities that are not a part of the original position description. Position descriptions contain a general description of a position and do not create any employment rights or entitlements.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.410</num>
      <heading>Employment At-Will</heading>
      <text>Employees, with the exception of certain contracted employees, are hired for an indefinite and unspecified duration and are not guaranteed employment for any specified length of time. As such, either the BFGC or an employee can terminate the employment relationship at-will, at any time. In addition, the BFGC can modify, amend, supplement or delete terms and conditions of employment relationship at-will, at any time, with or without cause or advance notice.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.5</num>
    <heading>Employment</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.501</num>
      <heading>Work Site Accommodations</heading>
      <text>The BFGC is exempted from the federal and state offered definition of an employer as provided by the American's with Disabilities Act, 42 USC § 12111 (5) (B).  However, as a matter of its own internal policies the BFGC discourages discrimination against persons with disabilities and when possible seeks to accommodate persons with disabilities on the job. Whenever possible, we will make reasonable accommodations for individuals with disabilities. Employees who would like to request a reasonable accommodation should contact the General Manager.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.502</num>
      <heading>Personnel Files</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Management will create and maintain a personnel file for each employee beginning at the time of employment. These files are the sole property of the BFGC and are deemed confidential.  An employee or his or her representative if designated in writing may inspect his or her personnel file.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>It is important that personnel files accurately reflect each employee's personal information. Employees are expected to inform the BFGC of any change in name, address, phone number, home and/or address, marital status, number of dependents or emergency contact information.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.503</num>
      <heading>Attendance/ Hours Of Work</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervisors will provide employees with their work schedule. Should an employee have any questions regarding his/ her work schedule, the employee should contact their supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All employees must punch in using the BFGC time clock. No employee shall knowingly punch or allow another employee to punch his or her timecard. Violation of this timecard protocol may lead to disciplinary action up to and including termination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All timecards are the property of the BFGC.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Employees who will be late to or absent from work should notify their supervisor in advance, or as soon as practicable in the event of an emergency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Absenteeism without excuse will not be tolerated. Chronic absenteeism will result in disciplinary action up to and including termination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Employees who need to leave early, for illness or otherwise, should inform a supervisor before departure. Unauthorized departures may result in disciplinary action up to and including termination.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.504</num>
      <heading>Tardiness</heading>
      <text>Employees are expected to arrive on time and ready for work. An employee who arrives five minutes after their scheduled arrival time is considered tardy. We recognize that situations arise which hinder punctuality; regardless, excessive tardiness is prohibited, and may be subject to discipline.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.505</num>
      <heading>Break Periods</heading>
      <text>When working conditions permit, and pending a supervisor's approval, employees are entitled to one paid 15-minute break for every four hours worked. Meal periods are unpaid and are for 30 minutes and must be approved by a supervisor.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.506</num>
      <heading>Inclement Weather</heading>
      <text>Work will be based upon weather conditions. All workers will be notified prior to start time by management.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.507</num>
      <heading>Paychecks</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The pay period for the BFGC is Sunday through Saturday. Paychecks are distributed every two (2) weeks by direct deposit to a banking institution of the employee's choice or by a paycheck. If the pay date lands on a holiday, paychecks will be distributed on the closest business day after the holiday.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The paycheck will reflect work performed for the previous pay period. Paychecks include salary or wages earned less any mandatory or elected deductions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notify a supervisor if the paycheck appears to be inaccurate or if it has been misplaced.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Advances on paycheck are not permitted.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.508</num>
      <heading>Resignations</heading>
      <text>We recognize that personal situations may arise which require Employee to resign from their position of employment. Should this occur, we request that the employee provide management two (2) weeks of notice in writing.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.6</num>
    <heading>Wages</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.601</num>
      <heading>Wage Classifications</heading>
      <text>The BFGC Corporation establishes wage and salary classifications for each position based on many factors, including, but not limited to position category, education, experience, knowledge, ability and level of responsibility.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.602</num>
      <heading>Temporary Increases</heading>
      <text>Management who obtains prior authorization of management may temporarily increase the pay rate of an employee during the time that the employee is temporarily performing the duties of a position with a higher salary range. Any increase will cease upon removal of the conditions that warranted the increase.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.603</num>
      <heading>Employer Payroll Deductions</heading>
      <text>Various payroll deductions are made each payday to comply with applicable laws, including but not limited to federal and state income tax withholding and social security. At the end of each calendar year, the BFGC will provide each employee with a Wage and Tax Statement (W-2) form. This statement summarizes employee income and deductions for the year.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.604</num>
      <heading>Bank Deposits Or Payroll Deductions</heading>
      <text>In addition, the BFGC may make deductions from Employees' paychecks in accordance with orders issued by a court of competent jurisdiction. Employees should contact the Accounting Department with any questions.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.605</num>
      <heading>Workers' Compensation</heading>
      <text>The BFGC carries insurance to cover the cost of work-incurred injury or illness.  Benefits help pay for employees' medical treatment and a portion of any income lost while recovering.  If an employee is injured or becomes ill as a result of his/her job, it is the employee's responsibility to immediately notify a supervisor of their injury in order to receive benefits. Report every illness or injury to a supervisor, regardless of how minor it appears. Management will advise the employee of the procedure for submitting a workers' compensation claim. If necessary, injured employees will be referred to a medical care facility. Failure to report a work-related illness or injury promptly could result in a denial of benefits. An employee's report should contain as many details as possible, including the date, time, description of the illness or injury , and the names of any witnesses.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.7</num>
    <heading>Benefits</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.701</num>
      <heading>Employee Merchandise Privileges</heading>
      <text>Employees may purchase golf merchandise in the Golf Shop at a 30% discount. Employees may not use this privilege to purchase for non-employees. Merchandise must be paid for at the time of purchase. Already discounted merchandise in the Golf Shop will not be eligible for the 30% employee discount unless noted by the General Manager.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.702</num>
      <heading>Employee Golf Privileges</heading>
      <text>Employees are offered golf privileges at no cost during off peak hours.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Tee times must be set and approved by golf operations staff.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Employees must check in with the Golf Shop prior to playing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Employees are allowed one free guest round per week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Employees must be playing with their guest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Situational exceptions can be granted during peak hours if the tee times go unused by customers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Employee tee times could be canceled in the event that tee time is not available to customers.</text>
        <text>As an employee with these golfing privileges you are representing BFGC while you are on the property. If bringing guests, you will be responsible for their adherence to our polices and their conduct.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.8</num>
    <heading>Expectations And Conduct</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.801</num>
      <heading>General Statement Of Expectations And Conduct</heading>
      <text>All Employees must conduct themselves in a manner, which is kind, courteous, ethical and respectful to all members of the public, including fellow employees. In all instances, employees must exercise good judgment and conduct themselves with the highest degree of professionalism. This ensures the work environment is safe, comfortable and productive. General cooperation between workers and supervisors is expected.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.802</num>
      <heading>Political Activity</heading>
      <text>Employees shall not directly or indirectly use their authority, influence or political aspirations to compel individuals to participate or not participate in Tribal political activity and/or election processes. Campaign buttons, posters, or apparel related to tribal political activity is prohibited at the workplace, and distributing literature, emailing, and circulating petitions related thereto during work time or in work areas is strictly prohibited. In addition, employees shall not use the BFGC property and services to influence individuals to participate or not participate in the Tribal election process.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.803</num>
      <heading>Non-Harassment Policy/Non-Discrimination Policy</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>BFGC prohibits discrimination or harassmentbased on race, color, religion, creed, sex, national origin, age, disability, marital status, veteran status or any other status protected by applicable law.  Each employee has the right to work in a professional atmosphere that promotes equal employment opportunity and is free from discriminatory practices, including, without limitation harassment.  Consistent with its workplace policy of equal employment opportunity, BFGC prohibits and will not tolerate harassment on the basis of race, color, religion, creed, sex, national origin, age, disability, marital status, veteran status or any other status protected by applicable law.  Violations of this policy will not be tolerated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any employee who feels that he or she has been harassed or discriminated against or has witnessed or become aware of discrimination or harassment in violation of these policies, should bring the matter to the immediate attention of his or her supervisor or the General Manager.  We will promptly investigate all allegations of discrimination and harassment and take action as appropriate based on the outcome of the investigation.  An investigation and its results will be treated as confidential to the extent feasible and we will take appropriate action based on the outcome of the investigation.  No employee will be retaliated against for making a</text>
      </para>
      <text>complaint in good faith regarding a violation of these policies.  If an employee feels he/she has been retaliated against, the employee should file a complaint using the procedures set forth above.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.804</num>
      <heading>Drug Free/Alcohol Free Environment</heading>
      <text>Employees are prohibited from unlawfully consuming, distributing, possessing, selling, or using controlled substances while on duty.  In addition, employees may not be under the influence of any controlled substance such as drugs or alcohol, while at work, on BFGC premises or engaged in company business.  Prescription drugs or over-the counter medications, taken as prescribed, are the exception to the policy.</text>
      <text>Anyone violating this policy may be subject to disciplinary action, up to and including termination.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.805</num>
      <heading>Drug And Alcohol Testing Procedures</heading>
      <text>Drug tests require laboratory testing as provided by the Mandatory guidelines for Federal Workplace Drug Testing Programs pursuant to 94 FR 28101, May 15, 2015 as amended, as minimum standards for the following classes of drug and correlative cutoff concentrations: Cocaine; Opiates including opium and codeine derivatives such as Oxycodone, Oxymorphone, Hydrocodone, Hydromorphone; Amphetamines and Methamphetamines including Methylenedioxyamphetamine (MDA) and Methylenedioxyethylamphetamine (MDEA); Phencyclidine (PCP). Nothing precludes the Human Resource Director, or designee, from testing for substances which are not included on this list, should the General Manager, or designee, determine it is in the best interests of the Corporation to include substances which are not listed above to ensure a drug free workplace. Employees are encouraged to contact the Human Resources designee, with any questions regarding drug and alcohol testing. Failure or refusal to participate in an employer-directed drug test is considered insubordination and the employee will be terminated for insubordination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><u>General Drug and Alcohol Testing Procedures</u>. In cases where an employee is required to undergo testing for the presence of alcohol or drugs (pre-employment, probable cause, and post-accident) the following procedures shall apply:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>LCO-CHC using a licensed laboratory of the LCO-CHC choice that conducts substance abuse testing that is deemed appropriate by the BFGC Board of Directors for business purposes; i.e., screening and confirmatory testing, will take a sufficient sample to assure that confirmation testing can occur in the event of an initial positive test result. The initial cost for this testing will be incurred by the BFGC.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The laboratory evaluation of the samples will be carried out by a laboratory that is contracted with the LCO-CHC and is certified by either the College of American Pathologists or the National Institute on Drug Abuse.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In the event of a positive test result, a confirmation test will be performed by a laboratory specified in subs. (b) above, using the original sample (not a new sample). The confirmation test will be based on a different analytical method of higher analytical certainty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The employee within two (2) working days of the results must request any further confirmation testing (using the original sample) by a laboratory specified in subs. 1(a) above, in writing. Costs of confirmation testing incurred will be paid by the employee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The results of any drug or alcohol tests shall be kept confidential, except information shall by Management as deemed necessary. All policies regarding employee personnel records shall be strictly adhered to and followed in accordance with the provisions of this Manual.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A portable breath test (PBT) conducted by a Class 1 PBT Certified person of the LCO-CHC choice that is deemed appropriate by BFGC Board of Directors for business purposes shall be utilized for alcohol testing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><u>Pre-Employment Testing</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant for employment will be required to undergo testing for illegal drugs and prescribed medication for which they do not have a valid prescription as a condition of employment.  If the applicant is suspected to be under the influence of alcohol at the time of their pre-employment drug screen, a PBT may be requested.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Applicants who test positive for alcohol, illegal drugs, and/or prescribed medication for which they do not have a valid prescription, shall be denied employment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An applicant who initially declines a drug test will be denied employment and not eligible for employment for 90 days.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text><u>Probable Cause Testing Procedures</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon a finding by an employee's supervisor that there is probable cause that the employee is either under the influence of alcohol (under the influence shall mean a blood alcohol concentration of 0.02 grams of alcohol per 100 milliliters of a person's blood or while the person has 0.02 grams of alcohol per 210 liters of a person's breath) or drug abuse that is impairing the employee's ability to carry out job-related activities, the employee shall be required to be tested for the presence of drugs or alcohol pursuant to subs. (c), below. A finding of probable cause and directive requiring the employee to submit to testing for drugs or alcohol must be in writing signed by the employee's supervisor. The probable cause finding must be supported by evidence of specific, personal observations concerning job performance, appearance, behavior, speech, or bodily odors of the employee. If hearsay information is received, such information must be corroborated by personal observations, or observations and evaluation by management, or designee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Once an employee's supervisor has determined that probable cause pursuant to subs. (a), above exists, the employee's supervisor shall immediately contact the General Manager or designee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Upon receiving contact from an employee's supervisor, the General Manager or designee shall have the employee drug tested and if alcohol related have the employee submit to a portable breath test (PBT) conducted by a Class 1 PBT Certified person. If the employee refuses to take a test (including but not limited to a drug test, drug urine test, or PBT test) after being required to do so, the employee is thereby insubordinate and considered to be in violation of the Drug Testing Policy and shall be terminated<em>.</em></text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Upon receipt of a positive test result, the employee shall be immediately relieved of their duty station and will be subject to disciplinary action, and the positive test sample will be sent for a confirmation test result pursuant to subs. (1) above. In all cases, an employee may face legal consequences for his/her actions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text><u>Post-Accident Testing Procedures</u>.</text>
        <text>It is the BFGC policy that an alcohol and drug test will be given to any team member involved in a work-related accident or injury event requiring professional medical treatment (EMT, paramedics, and other professional medical providers) for her/himself, another team member or guest. A work-related injury is an accident while on the clock and performing a work-related duty whether on property or off property so long as the act of which was being done at the time of the incident was for the purpose of work.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The team member must report to the General Manager, or designee within eight hours (regardless of time of day or day of week) of the reported accident or injury unless they are still under the care of a professional medical provider.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The General Manager, or designee shall have the employee drug tested and if alcohol related have the employee submit to a portable breath test (PBT) conducted by a Class 1 PBT Certified person. If the employee refuses to take a test (including but not limited to a drug test, drug urine test, or PBT test) after being required to do so, the employee is thereby insubordinate and considered to be in violation of the Drug Testing Policy and shall be terminated<em>.</em> A team member who receives a negative test result will immediately report back to their department.  A team member who receives a positive test result must submit to a second test.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Five (5) minutes following the Preliminary Test, the team member will receive a second Breathalyzer test.  A team member who receives a negative test result will immediately report back to their department. A team member who tests positive on the Second Breathalyzer Test will be in violation of the company Drug-Free Workplace policy.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A team member whose alcohol test has a positive Blood Alcohol Concentration (BAC) reading of .01 to .029 will be sent home for the day. If a team member is 0.03 or higher, and/or the drug test is positive for a substance they admit not having permission to take, is considered in violation of the employer's Drug-Free Workplace policy. A team member will be offered a ride home if they are sent home for a positive Preliminary Breathalyzer Test (PBT).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Upon receiving a presumptive positive result of the first drug test, the General Manager, or designee will seal the sample to be sent to the lab for confirmation. Every effort will be made to keep this information confidential.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.806</num>
      <heading>Inspection And Search</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The BFGC has the authority to inspect or search the entire work-place, including, but not limited to any office or desk when there are reasonable grounds for suspecting that the search will turn-up evidence that an employee violated any provision of this manual or otherwise engaged in work-related misconduct.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The BFGC has the authority to inspect or search, when the inspection or search is necessary for non-investigatory work-related purpose, including locating and retrieving any information from a location within the work place.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The BFGC has the authority to inspect or search any employee's personal possessions located within the work place when there are reasonable grounds for suspecting that the search will turn-up evidence that the employee violated any provision of this manual or otherwise engaged in work-related misconduct.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If an employee is found to be in possession of any item or substance prohibited by this manual or fail to comply with any inspection or search conducted in accordance with this manual, the employee will be subject to appropriate disciplinary action, up to and including termination. Any illegal substances that are found, in the course of an inspection or search, will be turned over to law enforcement.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.807</num>
      <heading>Confidentiality</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the course of performing duties for the BFGC, employees may obtain or become aware of confidential information, such as personnel, financial and legal information of the BFGC its operations and employees, including but not limited to information encompassed in any reports, mailing lists, proposals, marketing plans, financial projections, vendor or subcontractor quotes, financial data and any and all concepts or ideas, materials or information related to the business, products, or services of the BFGC or its customers and vendors ("Confidential Information").</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Employees must hold all Confidential Information in strict confidence and shall not directly or indirectly disclose Confidential Information or permit the release thereof to any outside person or entity except as necessary to perform employment duties or as otherwise required by law. If any question arises about whether information must be treated as confidential, employees must treat such information as confidential until confirmed otherwise by their supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Employees also must not use or release, directly or indirectly, any proprietary information or trade secrets of the BFGC without prior authorization from their supervisor. Trade secrets include any formula, pattern or devise of compilation of information which is used in the BFGC's business or operations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Violations of confidentiality, including the disclosure of confidential information (verbal, written or documents) as defined under this section shall be subject to discipline, up to and including termination.  The Tribe reserves the right to prosecute any violations to fullest extent allowed under tribal, state or federal law.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.808</num>
      <heading>Dress And Appearance</heading>
      <text>An employee's personal appearance and hygiene is a reflection on BFGC's character. Employees must dress and groom themselves in accordance with appropriate social and business standards. In addition, employees must maintain good personal hygiene. Management retains the right to request any employee to change his or her mode of dress or grooming if deemed provocative or otherwise inappropriate.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.809</num>
      <heading>Smoking</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>BFGC is dedicated to providing a healthy, comfortable and productive work environment for all employees and guests. In response to the growing concern about second-hand smoke, all BFGC facilities are smoke-free environments. Employees should never smoke while on duty. No employees should ever smoke in the presence of a guest. Do not smoke in or near a building or public area. Please use the provided containers for disposal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Nothing in this policy shall be deemed to limit or interfere with the use of tobacco at traditional ceremonies and cultural functions.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.810</num>
      <heading>Internet And Telephones</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All electronic and telephonic communication systems and all communications and information transmitted by, received from, or stored in these systems are the property of the BFGC and as such are to be used solely for job-related purposes. The use of any software and business equipment, including, but not limited to, e-mail, internet access, facsimile machines, computers, telephones (land lines and cellular phones) and copy machines for private purposes is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No employee may use a pass code or voice-mail access code that has not been issued to that employee or that is unknown to the BFGC. Moreover, improper use of the e-mail system (<em>e.g.</em>, distributing offensive jokes or remarks) will not be tolerated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Employees shall not use the BFGC Corporation's internet, voice mail and e-mail Resources, phones and other systems in a prohibited manner, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To transmit, view, retrieve, or store any communications of a discriminatory or harassing nature or materials that are considered obscene or pornographic;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To access pornographic internet sites, display or print any associated materials, pictures and cartoons;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To harass or transmit messages with derogatory or inflammatory remarks about an individual's race, sex (including pregnancy), age, disability, religion, national origin or physical attributes or transmit abusive, profane or offensive language;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For non-business, personal or private use, including but not limited to game playing and personal communication not associated with business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>To disclose any confidential or proprietary information except where such disclosure is authorized or permitted in this personnel policy and procedural manual.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Employees shall not use the BFGC's internet, voice mail and e-mail Resources and other systems and equipment, including but not limited to computer hardware, software, copier, fax machine and postage machine in a manner that is contrary to the provisions of any purchase or lease contract, such as unlawful copying of computer software.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding the BFGC's right to retrieve and read any voice or electronic mail messages, such messages should be treated as confidential by other employees and accessed only by the intended recipient. Employees are not authorized to retrieve or read any voice or e-mail messages that are not sent to them. Any exception to this policy must receive prior written approval by Management.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>BFGC may monitor, record and listen to all internet, e-mail and voice mail usage, to assure compliance with its policies, for cost analysis and for legitimate business purposes.  Thus, the BFGC may listen to, access and disclose any information in the electronic communication and telephone systems, even such information or communication protected by an employee's personal password, at any time, with or without notice to the employee. Employees have no expectation of privacy in connection with the use of these systems, or the transmission, receipt or storage of information in such systems.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.811</num>
      <heading>Bfgc Property</heading>
      <text>BFGC property, such as equipment, vehicles, telephones, computers and software, is not for private use.  These devices are to be used strictly for company business and are not permitted off grounds unless authorized.  BFGC property must be used in the manner for which it was intended.  Upon termination, employees are required to surrender any company property they possess.  Groundskeeper and maintenance staff will receive training on the operation and use of all equipment required for the performance of their duties and are required to operate the equipment in the appropriate and safe manner.</text>
      <text>BFGC computers, internet and emails are a privileged resource, and must be used only to complete essential job-related functions.  Files or programs stored on company computers may not be copied for personal use. Employees are reminded that they should have no expectation of privacy in their use of company computers.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.812</num>
      <heading>Privacy</heading>
      <text>Employees and employers share a relationship based on trust and mutual respect.  However, the company retains the right to access all BFGC property including vehicles, employee lockers, computers, desks, file cabinets, storage facilities, and files and folders, electronic or otherwise, at any time.  Employees should not entertain any expectation of privacy when on company grounds or while using company property.</text>
      <text>All documents, files, voice-mails and electronic information, including e-mails and other communications created, received or maintained on or through BFGC property are the property of the BFGC, not the employee.  Therefore, employees should have no expectation of privacy over those files or documents.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.813</num>
      <heading>Workplace Violence</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The BFGC is concerned about the increased violence in society, which has also filtered into many workplaces, and has taken steps to help prevent incidents of violence from occurring at its facilities. It is our policy to expressly prohibit any acts or threats of violence against any employee in or about our facilities or elsewhere at any time. We will not condone any acts or threats of violence against our employees, customers, or visitors on the BFGC's property at any time or while they are engaged in business with or on behalf of the BFGC, on or off our premises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In keeping with the spirit and intent of this policy, and to ensure the objectives in this regard are attained, the BFGC is committed to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To provide a safe and healthful work environment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To take prompt remedial action, up to and including immediate termination, against any employee who engages in any threatening behavior or acts of violence or who uses any obscene, abusive, or threatening language or gestures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To take appropriate action when dealing with customers, former employees, or visitors to our property who engage in such behavior. Such action may include notifying the police or other law enforcement personnel and prosecuting violators of this policy to the maximum extent of the law;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>To establish viable security measures to ensure that the BFGC's facilities are safe and secure to the maximum extent possible and to properly handle access to the BFGC's facilities by the public, off-duty employees, and former employees.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Employees, former employees, customers and visitors shall not bring or possess unauthorized firearms or other weapons onto the BFGC's premises. Any employee who displays a tendency to engage in violent, abusive, or threatening behavior or who otherwise engages in behavior that the BFGC, in its sole discretion, deems offensive or inappropriate, or who possesses a firearm or weapon in violation of this policy will be subject to disciplinary action, up to and including termination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Employees have a "duty to warn" the BFGC of any suspicious workplace activity or situations or incidents that they observe or that they are aware of that involve other employees, former employees, customers, or visitors and that appear problematic. This includes, for example, threats or acts of violence, aggressive behavior, offensive acts, threatening or offensive comments or remarks, and the like. Employee reports made pursuant to this policy will be held in confidence to the maximum possible extent. The BFGC will not condone any form of retaliation against any employee for making a report under this policy.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.814</num>
      <heading>Off-Duty Misconduct</heading>
      <text>Employees shall not engage in off-duty misconduct which is deemed detrimental to the BFGC. While it is impossible to predict every detrimental situation, the BFGC may determine that off-duty misconduct is averse to the BFGC, because it is serious in nature; is at odds with an employee's job duties; or is notorious and has the potential to discredit the BFGC.  Any arrest shall be reported to the General Manager within 72 hours.  Any arrest shall be subject to review by the General Manager and may include discipline including a suspension or termination depending on the determination and severity of the allegations leading to an arrest.  An arrest and conviction related to misconduct shall be subject to discipline which may include termination.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.815</num>
      <heading>Employee Social Media Policy</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>While BFGC encourages its employees to enjoy and make good use of their off-duty time, certain activities on the part of employees may become a concern if they have the effect of impairing the work of any employee; harassing, demeaning, or creating a hostile work environment for any employee; disrupting the smooth and orderly flow of work; or harming the goodwill and reputation of the BFGC. In the area of social media (print, broadcast, digital, and online services such as Facebook, LinkedIn, Instagram, Plaxo, and Twitter, among others), employees may use such media in any way they choose as long as such use does not produce the adverse consequences noted above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An employee shall be subject to disciplinary action, up to and including termination of employment, depending upon the severity and repeat nature of the offense, if an employee publishes any personal information about another employee of the BFGC in any public medium (print, broadcast, digital, or online) that produces the adverse consequences noted in subs. (1), above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No employee may use the BFGC's equipment or facilities for furtherance of non-work-related social media related activities or relationships without the express advance permission of the General Manager.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Employees who conduct themselves in such a way that their social media related actions toward and relationships with each other interfere with or damage work relationships, disrupt the flow of work, or cause unfavorable publicity in the community, should be concerned that their conduct may be inconsistent with one or more of the provisions of this policy. In such a situation, the employees involved should request guidance from management to discuss the possibility of a resolution that would avoid such problems. Depending upon the circumstances, failure to seek such guidance may be considered evidence of intent to conceal a violation of the policy and to hinder an investigation into the matter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Use of social media that involves any kind of criminal activity or harms the rights of others may result in criminal prosecution or civil liability to those harmed, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Social media access and use involving BFGC equipment and Resources are subject to the General Manager.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The provisions in this policy are not intended to restrict communications regarding the terms and conditions of the workplace.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>How an employee uses social media is not a matter of concern as long as it is consistent with the aforementioned provisions on this policy. Employees may address any questions on this policy to the General Manager.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.816</num>
      <heading>Children In The Workplace</heading>
      <text>The presence of children in the workplace is discouraged because it can be disruptive to other employees and customers. Management has the authority to prohibit an employee from having a child at the workplace. Please contact the General Manager to make exceptions to this rule.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.9</num>
    <heading>Safety</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.901</num>
      <heading>General Rules</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>BFGC takes every reasonable precaution to ensure that employees have a safe working environment.  Safety measures and rules are in place for the protection of all employees.  Ultimately, it is the responsibility of each employee to help prevent accidents.  Employees should use all safety and protective equipment provided to them and maintain work areas in a safe and orderly manner, free from hazardous conditions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Employees who observe an unsafe practice or condition should report to a supervisor or the General Manager immediately.  Employees are prohibited from making threats against anyone in connection with his/her work or engaging in violent activities while in the employment of the company.  Any questions regarding safety and safe practices should be directed to the General Manager.</text>
      </para>
      <text>In the event of an accident or injury, regardless of how minor, employees must notify a supervisor immediately.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.902</num>
      <heading>Accidents Or Injuries</heading>
      <text>If an accident or injury occurs, until medical help arrives employees should try to provide aid and comfort to the injured person. In the event of an accident or injury, regardless of how minor, employees must notify a supervisor immediately. Employees should try to keep the circumstances of any accident or injury fresh in their minds so that the incident can be reported accurately and to provide information that may prevent a repeated incident. The employee will be required to fill out an incident report form.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.903</num>
      <heading>Hazardous Materials</heading>
      <text>The BFGC complies with all applicable "Right to Know" laws, which means employees will be made aware of any chemical hazards at the workplace. Employees will also receive special training concerning the labeling, handling and disposal of hazardous substances, and what steps should be taken in the event of a spill or release.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.10</num>
    <heading>Problem Solving</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.1001</num>
      <heading>General Statement</heading>
      <text>When people work closely together it is only natural that problems, questions or conflict may sometimes arise. It is in the best interest of BFGC and all employees that these issues be resolved as quickly and fairly as possible; therefore, the BFGC supports an "open-communication policy" to encourage addressing these issues.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.1002</num>
      <heading>Open Communication Policy</heading>
      <text>BFGC takes employees concerns and problems seriously. We value each employee and strive to provide a positive work experience. Employees are encouraged to bring any workplace concerns or problems they might have or know about to their supervisor or some other member of management.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.11</num>
    <heading>Disciplinary Action</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.1101</num>
      <heading>Grounds For Disciplinary Action</heading>
      <text>BFGC reserves the right to discipline and/or terminate any employee who violates company policies, practices or rules of conduct.  Poor performance and misconduct are also grounds for discipline or termination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following actions are unacceptable and considered grounds for disciplinary action. This list is not comprehensive; rather, it is meant merely as an example of the types of conduct that the company does not tolerate.  These actions include, but are not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Engaging in acts of discrimination or harassment in the workplace;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Possessing, distributing or being under the influence of illicit controlled substances;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Being under the influence of a controlled substance or alcohol at work, on BFGC premises, or while engaged in company business.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Unauthorized use of BFGC property or equipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Damage, destruction or theft of BFGC property, equipment or devices;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Removing BFGC property without prior authorization or disseminating BFGC information without authorization;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Falsification, misrepresentation, or omission of information; documents or records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Lying;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Insubordination or refusal to comply with directives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Failing to adequately perform job responsibilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Excessive or unexcused absenteeism or tardiness;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Disclosing confidential or proprietary BFGC information without permission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Illegal or violent activity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Falsifying injury reports or reasons for leave;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Possessing weapons on premises;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Disregard for safety and security procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>Disparaging or disrespecting supervisors and/or co-workers; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>Any other action or conduct that is inconsistent with BFGC policies, procedures, standards or expectations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.1102</num>
      <heading>Disciplinary Actions</heading>
      <text>Disciplinary action is any one of a number of options used to correct unacceptable behavior or actions.  Discipline may take the form of oral warnings, written warnings, suspension, demotion, discharge or some other disciplinary action. The course of action will be determined by BFGC at its sole discretion as it deems appropriate.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.1103</num>
      <heading>Termination</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Employment with the BFGC is on an at-will basis and may be terminated at any time.</text>
      </para>
      <text>BFGC retains the sole discretion to determine what behavior warrants disciplinary action and what type of disciplinary action will be imposed. The BFGC reserves the right to terminate employees at any time for any reason that does not violate applicable law with or without notice and with or without prior resort to other means of discipline.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All rights and privileges of employment terminate upon the date of separation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Terminated employees are required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Continue to work until the last scheduled day of employment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Return all files, documents, equipment, keys, access cards, or other property belonging to the BFGC that are in the employee's possession, custody or control. Failure to do so may result in the withholding of their final paycheck.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To participate in an exit interview ass requested by the General Manager.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.1104</num>
      <heading>No Right To Appeal</heading>
      <text>Each employee that has been disciplined or terminated will not have the right to appeal to the Tribal Court. All decisions made by the General Manager are FINAL.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
    <num>17.12</num>
    <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
    <section>
      <num>17.1201</num>
      <heading>Cash Handling Policy</heading>
      <text>The purpose of the cash handling policy is to ensure control and safekeeping of BFGC cash assets.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>17.1202</num>
      <heading>Cash Handling Procedures</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each employee that requires cash to conduct business will receive their cash daily from the General Manager or Office Manager.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The employee will count out their bank and have it verified by the General Manager or Office Manager.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the end of the employee's shift the employee will count their drawer and record this amount on a tally sheet.  The tally sheet and the cash will then be placed in a security bag with the employee's name, date and department written on the bag.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The employee will then give their bag to the General Manager or Office Manager to be placed in the large safe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In the event there is more than one employee working after 5 pm, the Employee in the Pro Shop will call the General Manager or Office Manager to come to the course when they are ready to close to secure the cash in the large safe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>When the Pro Shop attendant is the last to leave the course, the Pro Shop attendant will place their cash bag in the small safe.  Pro Shop employees will have their own code to enter the small safe room and the combination to the safe to either get their bank in the morning or secure their bank at night.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Office Manager will verify the cash each morning and reconcile it with the Tee Snap Cash and Summary report and make the appropriate deposit to the bank.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When total receipts do not equal the total deposit, the variance should be extended in the over/short line. The variance should never be added to or deducted from the starting cash in an attempt to balance receipts to deposits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In the event of a cash deposit shortage, the employee's wages will be deducted to cover register shortages.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Employee will be subject to discipline at the discretion of the General Manager or designee depending on the circumstances and regularity of any variances</text>
        <text class="center">
          <strong>PERSONNEL POLICIES AND PROCEDURES MANUAL</strong>
        </text>
        <text class="center">
          <strong>RECEIPT AND ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</strong>
        </text>
      </para>
      <text>I hereby acknowledge receipt of a copy of the Personnel Policies and Procedures of the BFGC. This personnel policy and procedural manual contains the policies and rules that apply to me. I agree to read the manual and follow it during my employment with the BFGC. I further understand the BFGB Board of Directors may amend this personnel policy and procedural manual at any time and that such changes will be communicated to me in writing.</text>
      <text>Employee Signature					Date</text>
      <text>Employee Name (Printed)</text>
      <text>Please keep a copy of this acknowledgement for your records.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
