<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2022-48">
  <num>2022-48</num>
  <heading>Amendment to Compensatory Time Sections of All Chapters under Title XIV of the LCOTCL</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2022-05-23</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2022-05-23</adopted>
    </history>
    <citatations/>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2022-48.pdf">Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2022-48</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians (“Tribe”) is a federally recognized Indian tribe organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. § 5101, et seq.; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, Section 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(n)">Article V, Section 1(n)</cite> of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: “regulate, by enactment of ordinances, the conduct of business within the territory of the band," <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(n)">Article V, Section 1(n)</cite>.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board duly enacted Title XIV and all of the Chapters contained under that title,  and is amending all Chapters under said title to remove the following language:</text>
      <text>
        <em>Time paid for PTO or other paid leave does not count as hours worked for purposes of calculating compensatory in a work week.</em>
      </text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that this amendment shall remove the above language from all Sections titled "Compensatory Time" in all Chapters under <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="XIV">Title XIV</cite>, of the LCOTCL.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>6</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>23<sup>rd</sup> day of May, 2022</u></strong>; that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>5</u></strong> members, <strong><u>0</u></strong> against, <strong><u>0</u></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution has not been rescinded or amended in any way.</text>
    <text>_______________________________________________</text>
    <text>Tweed Shuman, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
