<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2022-05">
  <num>2022-05</num>
  <heading>Amendment of Title XI, Chapter 7 of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code of Law Housing Authority Code</heading>
  <meta>
    <ordinance>Housing Authority Code of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</ordinance>
    <effective>2021-12-20</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2022-01-31</adopted>
    </history>
    <citatations/>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2022-05.pdf">Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2022-05</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians (“Tribe”) is a federally recognized Indian tribe organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. § 461, et seq.; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, Section 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, Section 1(l)</cite> and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(m)">(m)</cite> of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: “organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a housing authority, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the reservation” <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, Section 1 (l)</cite>;  and “delegate to subordinate boards, officers, committees or cooperative associations which are open to all members of the Band any of the foregoing powers, reserving the right to review any action taken by virtue of such delegated powers” <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(m)">Article V, Section 1 (m)</cite>.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board duly enacted the Housing Authority Code, as amended, for the purpose of providing adequate and affordable housing and housing services to low- and moderate- income Indian families and individuals within the Reservation and any other area served by the Tribe in compliance with the requirements, rules, and regulations of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-determination Act of 1996.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board determines that it is in the best interests of the Tribe to amend the Housing Authority Code.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the amendment found below to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="PRP|PRP.7">Title XI, Chapter 7</cite> of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code of Law “Housing Authority Code” shall be, and hereby are, enacted, effective December 20th 2021, as an ordinance of the Tribe, pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, Section 1(l)</cite> and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(m)">(m)</cite> of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and these sections as they exist at this time are hereby repealed in their entirety.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the following has been amended.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <text>
    <strong><u><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§PRP.7.5.060">§ 7.506</cite> Ineligibility for Admission</u>.</strong>
  </text>
  <text>
    <strong>Subsection (9) is amended as follows.</strong>
  </text>
  <text>
    <strong>Prior Subsection:</strong>
  </text>
  <text>(5) No person shall be allowed admission to housing, either as head of household or other member of household, who has been convicted of the illegal manufacture, sale, or distribution of a controlled substance, or possession with intent to manufacture, sell, or distribute a controlled substance;</text>
  <text>
    <strong>Amended Subsection:</strong>
  </text>
  <text>(5) No person shall be allowed admission to housing, either as head of household or other member of household, who has been convicted of the illegal manufacture, sale, or distribution of a controlled substance, or possession with intent to manufacture, sell, or distribute a controlled substance, unless granted pardon and forgiveness;</text>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom _ being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>31st day of January, 2022</u></strong>; that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of __ members, __ against, __ abstaining, and that said Resolution has not been rescinded or amended in any way.</text>
    <text>_______________________________________________</text>
    <text>Tweed Shuman, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
